<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-electric-chair/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032490/1887-04-17/ed-1/?sp=10&amp;q=Death+Dynamo+Electric+Chair+Capital+Punishment&amp;st=image&amp;r=-0.267,-0.077,1.535,1.535,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          "If the law i3 changed from hanging to
          death by electricity then it should and
          would bo made to include women as well as
          men. Any discrimination between the sexes
          would make the law unconstitutional."
          ""Would there b3 any objection to execut
          ing women with electricity.'"
          "No, sir; there would not. I think there
          would no longer be tho samo prejudico that
          thcro is now, because Imaging is a poor way
          of inflicting the death penalty."
          "How would you uso electricity?"
          "Just seo here," said Dr. Southwick,
          jumping up and .seating himself, in an arm
          chair. "Tho condemned man cansifc natur
          ally in a chair like this, placo his liands on
          the metal arms and converse with those
          around him. Tho metal plates would ba
          connected with a powerful d3namo and at
          tho proper moment somebody in another
          room would press a button, closo tho current
          and tho fatal shock would pass through tho
          body of the subject. Tho chargo would go
          straight through tho heart and lungs and
          penetrate the system, death instantly result
          ing. Tho expense of the apparatus with which
          to execute by electricity ia this city would
          bo about $150. Connection cculd bo made
          with the electric light station, and tho ex
          pense of an execution thereafter would bo of
          littlo consequence. It would not cost any
          more than a cigar to kill a condemned man
          after that. It would not bo necessary to
          maintain extensive and powerful machinery
          in nil tho prisons, anil it would bo vastly
          cheaper than hanging."
          "You believe then in electricity?'
          "Electricity Ls tho coming power. Death
          is instantaneous and tho body i not defaced.
          There is not tho morbidness of n hanging,
          which is a relic cf barbarism. Just seo a
          recent execution here Heman's I think it
          was when tho hanged man breathed fifteen
          minutes afteV the drop fell. If that is in
          stantaneous death then I would rather havo
          u lingering death."
          "Have you considered jwisons as a means
          of executing criminals''
          "Prussic acid has been raggested, but
          neither that nor garroting has met with any
          favor. A few havo advocated tho guillotine,
          but I thin!; it is a barbarous mode of causing
          death. Hardly any one favors hanging in
          preference to electricity,
          "I am heartily in favor of the application
          of electricity for tho purposes in question,
          for the reason that it is simple, sure and
          painless. 1 think that if the places of execu
          tion wero limited to two in this state, say
          ono at Auburn and ono at Sing Sing, the
          two stato prisons, and that all convicts as
          Foon as condemned to suffer tho death
          penalty should bo confined in ono of those
          two prisons (depending somewhat upon the
          locality of tho trial), it would be a vast im
          provement upon tho present method of hav
          ing tho criminal confined in the county jail
          till the daj- of execution."
          Regarding tho machinery to Iw used
          Senator llcl.lillan says: "Theso 'executions
          could take place in tho jail proper, in a room
          set apart for that purpose, with no appli
          ances save that of a chair, with tuo nana
          rest of each arm properly connected with
          an electric machine, in which tho condemned
          might bo seated and tho connection made by
          strapping a hand to the hand rest on each
          chair. There can bo no difficulty whatever
          in procuring a current of electricity of suffi
          cient strength to paralyze tho muscles of
          tho heart by this method. Indeed, tho cur
          rent that is used in this city for electric
          lighting purposes is of sufficient strength to
          absolutely dismember the body of nay human
          being, but a current of electricity of suffi
          cient strength to cause instantaneous death
          by passing from hand to hand through the
          heart wi'l not mark the body in tho least."
          San Vranelsco'a X"nr Trade.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86075267/1888-12-13/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Electrical+Electric+Chair+Capital+Punishment+Killing+Electricity+murderers+lightning</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          APTAN PROPOSED.
          gow Will Electrical Execu
          tions Be Accomplished?
          TlE LAST THING IN KILLING.
          How Various Nations Do Their Criminals
          to Death--New TYok State the Flrat
          commeunty to Adapt the Newest Thing
          in Capital PlUnihment.
          After Jan. 1, 1880, murderers in New York
          sate will depart this life on a streak of light
          ing. Any man who has been sentenced to
          death will go off. so quick that he won't
          know anything about it. The subject of
          putting murderers to death by electricity has
          been agitated in the Empire state for more
          than a year.
          After mature deliberation it was concluded
          that hanging would have to go.
          Hanging has been the fashionable mode of
          punishment for centuries, but a commission
          *appointed by Governor Hill concluded that it
          was too harrowing. They made a number
          of experiments, and finally decided upon
          electricity. A bill was passed by the legis
          lature, but-no provision was made as to the
          way the fluid was to be applied. Finally the
          Medico-legal society took the matter Uo, ap
          pointed a commission, and the result was
          that a particular form of applying the elec
          tricity was suggested. This way of killing
          off the refuse population will probably be
          used in New York state hereafter. Three
          ways of applying the fatal electricity were
          proposed, but none of them answered the
          purpose. One was passing the electri.
          iots city from wrist to
          wrist through the
          body, another
          was passing the
          current from the
          head to one of the
          wrists, the third
          Swas topassthecmu
          rent completely
          t through the prison.
          S1 etr's body from head
          to foot.
          c c m The objections to
          A CURRENT IN THE BRAIn these methods were
          that the prisoner might have convulsions.
          It was desired, of course, to take the utmost
          care of the prisoner. He was to die as pleas
          antly as possible. Then the attendant under
          this method might make a mistake and be
          struck himself.
          The commission finally concluded that the
          best way would be to have the current pass
          through the hoad from the top to the back of
          the neck. One electrode is fitted to the top
          of the prisoner's head, another placed in con
          tact with the small of his back. The top
          electrode connects with the positive pole, the
          bottom with the negative pole. A leathern
          rest holds the prisoner's head and bands
          keep him from moving. The current, in go
          ing from one electrode to another, does not
          keep in a straight line, but spreads out and
          goes through the entire brain. It resembles
          somewhat a bundle of faggots tied at the two
          ends and swelling out in the middle. The seat
          of consciousness being in the brain, and the
          headquarters for all the nerves being located
          there, it is of course as plain as day that,
          when an electro-motive force of 8, 30 volts
          is applied, the prisoner is bound to die. The
          great beauty of this system is that the pris
          oners don't know it either.
          Heroe we have a villain who is too bad to
          stay around and commit murder any more.
          Step up, ladies and gentlemen, and gazoon
          the wayitisdone. Here we have astouttable
          covered with rubber cloth and having holes
          around its borders for binding. Prisoner,
          come up here and lieon the table. Attendant,
          bind the prisoner to the table. Here is an
          electrode (the negative one) which comes up
          through the table and touches the small of
          the prisoner's back. Here we have a helmet,
          to which the other electrode is joined, and
          t helmet is put on the prisoner's head. The
          Wtrode now touches the top of the prison
          9~head, which has been moistened bywarm
          ater. Prisoner, are you ready? Then, let
          'cgo, Gallagher, and the thing is done. The
          man is as dead as a
          door nail. Another
          modification of this
          method is to let the
          prisoner sit in a
          chair. Some pris
          oners will undoubt
          edly prefer to sit
          in a chair, whleilo
          others who were
          born tired will pro- e'O
          for to lie at full
          length. Eerthinug THE DEATH APPARATUS.
          will be done in regard to the com ort of the
          prisoners, and their taste will be consulted
          in every particular.
          This, in brief, is the way the prisoners will
          "lick the bucket" after the 1st of January.
          When Elbridgo T. Gerry, Mathew Hale
          and Alfred P. Southwick wero appointed last
          winter to investigate the matter they took
          the trouble to look up the various methods of
          Panishment in different countries.
          Now, however, the main object in
          to get the prisoner out of the way as soon as
          possible. In order to understand how quick
          a man can die under the force of electricity,
          let us consider first how fast a man can think.
          Well, it takes just one-tenth of a second fora
          nerve to communicate with the brain, ac
          cording to Professor Hemholz Now Pro
          fessor Tyndall estimates that an electric dis
          charge occurs in one hundred thousandth of
          a second, or ten thousand times more rapidly
          than nerve transmission. So you see that it
          it were possible a man would die by the
          process described ten thousand times before
          his nerves would have time to communicate
          with his brain.
          Last winter, for the purpose of ascertain
          ing the effect of the electric light current on
          the action of the heart, the thorax of a
          chloroformed dog caught in Buffalo was
          opened, so that the lungs and heart could be
          seen in action by forcing respiration as in
          conscious life. At the instant when the cur
          rent passed through the heart it became a
          mass of quivering flesh. It was noticed that
          an attempt to breathe was made after the
          current was passed through the dog. This
          indicated that the brain had not lost its sus
          ceptibility to impressions, and shows that in
          execution the current should be passed
          through the center. It should not be for
          gotten, however, that the dog was from
          utffalo. The commission couldheaveselected
          no tougher subject than a Buffalo dog.
          There can be no question, however, that
          electricity is the thing to do the business.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86075267/1888-12-13/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Electrical+Electric+Chair+Capital+Punishment+Killing+Electricity+murderers+lightning&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.248,-0.075,1.496,1.496,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          APTAN PROPOSED.
          gow Will Electrical Execu
          tions Be Accomplished?
          TlE LAST THING IN KILLING.
          How Various Nations Do Their Criminals
          to Death--New TYok State the Flrat
          commeunty to Adapt the Newest Thing
          in Capital PlUnihment.
          After Jan. 1, 1880, murderers in New York
          sate will depart this life on a streak of light
          ing. Any man who has been sentenced to
          death will go off. so quick that he won't
          know anything about it. The subject of
          putting murderers to death by electricity has
          been agitated in the Empire state for more
          than a year.
          After mature deliberation it was concluded
          that hanging would have to go.
          Hanging has been the fashionable mode of
          punishment for centuries, but a commission
          *appointed by Governor Hill concluded that it
          was too harrowing. They made a number
          of experiments, and finally decided upon
          electricity. A bill was passed by the legis
          lature, but-no provision was made as to the
          way the fluid was to be applied. Finally the
          Medico-legal society took the matter Uo, ap
          pointed a commission, and the result was
          that a particular form of applying the elec
          tricity was suggested. This way of killing
          off the refuse population will probably be
          used in New York state hereafter. Three
          ways of applying the fatal electricity were
          proposed, but none of them answered the
          purpose. One was passing the electri.
          iots city from wrist to
          wrist through the
          body, another
          was passing the
          current from the
          head to one of the
          wrists, the third
          Swas topassthecmu
          rent completely
          t through the prison.
          S1 etr's body from head
          to foot.
          c c m The objections to
          A CURRENT IN THE BRAIn these methods were
          that the prisoner might have convulsions.
          It was desired, of course, to take the utmost
          care of the prisoner. He was to die as pleas
          antly as possible. Then the attendant under
          this method might make a mistake and be
          struck himself.
          The commission finally concluded that the
          best way would be to have the current pass
          through the hoad from the top to the back of
          the neck. One electrode is fitted to the top
          of the prisoner's head, another placed in con
          tact with the small of his back. The top
          electrode connects with the positive pole, the
          bottom with the negative pole. A leathern
          rest holds the prisoner's head and bands
          keep him from moving. The current, in go
          ing from one electrode to another, does not
          keep in a straight line, but spreads out and
          goes through the entire brain. It resembles
          somewhat a bundle of faggots tied at the two
          ends and swelling out in the middle. The seat
          of consciousness being in the brain, and the
          headquarters for all the nerves being located
          there, it is of course as plain as day that,
          when an electro-motive force of 8, 30 volts
          is applied, the prisoner is bound to die. The
          great beauty of this system is that the pris
          oners don't know it either.
          Heroe we have a villain who is too bad to
          stay around and commit murder any more.
          Step up, ladies and gentlemen, and gazoon
          the wayitisdone. Here we have astouttable
          covered with rubber cloth and having holes
          around its borders for binding. Prisoner,
          come up here and lieon the table. Attendant,
          bind the prisoner to the table. Here is an
          electrode (the negative one) which comes up
          through the table and touches the small of
          the prisoner's back. Here we have a helmet,
          to which the other electrode is joined, and
          t helmet is put on the prisoner's head. The
          Wtrode now touches the top of the prison
          9~head, which has been moistened bywarm
          ater. Prisoner, are you ready? Then, let
          'cgo, Gallagher, and the thing is done. The
          man is as dead as a
          door nail. Another
          modification of this
          method is to let the
          prisoner sit in a
          chair. Some pris
          oners will undoubt
          edly prefer to sit
          in a chair, whleilo
          others who were
          born tired will pro- e'O
          for to lie at full
          length. Eerthinug THE DEATH APPARATUS.
          will be done in regard to the com ort of the
          prisoners, and their taste will be consulted
          in every particular.
          This, in brief, is the way the prisoners will
          "lick the bucket" after the 1st of January.
          When Elbridgo T. Gerry, Mathew Hale
          and Alfred P. Southwick wero appointed last
          winter to investigate the matter they took
          the trouble to look up the various methods of
          Panishment in different countries.
          . In order to understand how quick
          a man can die under the force of electricity,
          let us consider first how fast a man can think.
          Well, it takes just one-tenth of a second fora
          nerve to communicate with the brain, ac
          cording to Professor Hemholz Now Pro
          fessor Tyndall estimates that an electric dis
          charge occurs in one hundred thousandth of
          a second, or ten thousand times more rapidly
          than nerve transmission. So you see that it
          it were possible a man would die by the
          process described ten thousand times before
          his nerves would have time to communicate
          with his brain.
          Last winter, for the purpose of ascertain
          ing the effect of the electric light current on
          the action of the heart, the thorax of a
          chloroformed dog caught in Buffalo was
          opened, so that the lungs and heart could be
          seen in action by forcing respiration as in
          conscious life. At the instant when the cur
          rent passed through the heart it became a
          mass of quivering flesh. It was noticed that
          an attempt to breathe was made after the
          current was passed through the dog. This
          indicated that the brain had not lost its sus
          ceptibility to impressions, and shows that in
          execution the current should be passed
          through the center. It should not be for
          gotten, however, that the dog was from
          utffalo. The commission couldheaveselected
          no tougher subject than a Buffalo dog.
          There can be no question, however, that
          electricity is the thing to do the business.
          HE LET HIMSELF DROP.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84025891/1895-09-07/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=Lizzie+Halliday+Lunatic+Asylum+Murder+Electricity&amp;st=image&amp;r=-0.306,-0.081,1.611,1.611,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          She next stole a horse. She was sent
          to an insane asylum, but discharged as
          aured, and in September, 1893, the bodies
          Df Margaret McQuillan and her daughter
          Sarah, whom she had lured from their
          lome in Newburg, were found under the
          oarn. Si s had shot them and buried
          :hem. The corpse of her husband was
          found a little while afterwards, riddled
          with bullels, buried under the house.
          The woman was plaoed In the jail at
          Monticello: There, she had frequent vio
          lent outbreaks, attacking the jailer's wife
          n one occasion. She also set fire to her cot
          md later hanged herself to her cell door.
          Then ahe was put on trial at Monticello,
          found guilty of murder In the first decree
          md sentenced to be killed by electricity.
          3he was removed to Dannemora gagged
          md bound on account of her violence.
          Governor Flower commuted her sentence
          ;o life imprisonment on the ground that she
          xras insane, and she was transferred to
          the lunatic asylum at Matteawan.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016758/1899-06-01/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Death+Chair+Penalty+Capital+Punishment+Murder</id>
        <rel>0</rel>

      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84028140/1901-10-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Repentance+Czolgosz+Electric+Chair+Electrocuted+Deadly+Current</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          In the Electric Chair.
          Cowardice Quivered on His Lips, But Unsustained by Prayer or Hope of Eter
          nity He Felt the Mask of Death Upon His Face and Passed to Oblivion,
          Hated and Despised.
          Auburn, N. Y., Oct 20.-(Spl.)-Loon
          F. Czolgosz, alias Fred Nieman, was
          successfully electrocuted at Auburn
          prison this morning. He was pro
          nouncod dead at 7:10:15 a. in.
          With the purely animal courage that
          bud sustained blm and the Innate cow
          ard within him struggling to his lips,
          the youthful murderer, hated by tho
          nation and tho world at largo, paid the
          ponalty for his crime.
          Ho took tho chair at 7:15 and In less
          itlmo than It takes to tell it, tho deadly
          current had paaHod through his body,
          rubblnrr 'nmfeshla miserable existence
          with merciful and unerring swiftness.
          Seated In tho chair, with the fatal
          curroilt about to bo applied, Czolgosz,
          V facing tho witnesses said;
          "I shot the President becauso 1
          thought It would benefit good work
          ing people by ridding them of abom
          inations. I am not sorry for my
          crime."
          During Oils time tho attendants wcro
          busy strapping him to tho enalr. His
          last words were: "I am heartily sorry
          I did not see my father."
          This was said after tho strap had
          been drawn across his face, yet his
          words were heard distinctly by all tho
          witnesses in tho roomi Ho went to
          his death unsupported by tho com
          forting thought that ho had mado
          pence with his God.
          For Uie lrst time In the history of
          the prison a condemned man marched
          to tlie fatal chair unaccorupnnicd by a
          Spiritual advisor, Spiritual aid hod
          been offered hUn, but ho scorned all
          entreaties. Ho wanted no one to prny
          tpt his soiuV
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1903-10-01/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Chair+Fifteen+Minutes+Van+Wormers+Electrocuted+Willis+Frederick+Burton+Electric</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          3 VAN WORMERS J
          J
          OlE IN THE CHAIR
          IN FifTEEN MINUTES
          The Brothers Are Electrocuted One
          After the Other with Marvellous
          i Speed Without a Hitch in the Triple
          Tragedy Each Displaying Nerve
          I Willis the Eldest Was the First tcTDie
          Then Came Frederick the Youngest
          I 1 and Burton Most Composed and De
          l termined of All Was the Last
          I
          I I
          QUICK WORK OF DEATH SHOCKS
          WILLIS VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
          113430 The current was turned into his body one
          minute later He was dead at 1137
          FRBDBRICK VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
          11413O At 1142 the current was turned on He was
          declared dead at 114330
          I
          BURTON VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
          1147 The currant wai turned on at 114730 He was
          declared dead at 114830
          lbe actual time of the triple execution was less than
          fifteen minutes
          1
          Special to The Evening World
          DANNEMORA Oct tThe lives of the three Van Wormer boys
          p tyho were condemned to death for the murder of Peter Hallenbeck were
          forfeited to the tw In extraordinarily quick time today The ceremony
          1 of shocking them to death in the elecfrtfc chair consumed but thirty sec
          I onds over fifteen minutes That length of time elapsed from the moment
          when y1illis Van Wormer left his cell and started for the death chamber
          until the physicians pronounced Burton Van Wormer the last of the trio
          deadTherewas
          Therewas not a hitch in the proaling The fascinated witnesse
          sat and watchedandvscarcely breathed as ihe men were led in killed anc
          carried out with strict adherence to a prearranged time table The boy
          died with the most surprising composure None can tell the horrible
          ordeal through which Burton Van Wormer passed as he awaited his turn
          3Ut he showec no sign of fear when led out to face his doom
          GLOOM TO BEFIT TIlE OCCASION
          It was an eternity of gloom within the purlieus ot Clinton walls am
          black ae an Ink well upside down
          t At 1135 oclock five minutes earlier than usual the prison whistle
          ii which regulates the life of tho penitentiary and marks the uprisings an
          downslttlngs of tho people in the village of Dannemora gave fortlh a
          shrieking blast The whirring wheels and belts in tho factories came to c
          rest and the time of tho triple killing had arrived A boll rang In the
          Wardens office and a guard appeared at tho door and beckoned to the wit
          nesses Two by two they followed him to the rear of the administration
          I building through the alleyway which Is between the north tter of con
          demned cells and the structure wall
          r As they passed a mumble Of voices came from the quarters of the
          doomed Father Beranger who hail been so attentive to the condemned
          f men was with the Van Wjornjors giving promises of hope and receiving
          responses of belief
          Tho ears ot theboys must have heard the tread of many feet going
          by The death watchers said after the legal tragedy had ended that they
          i heard and that their limbs shook
          Soon tho crowd was in the chamber of death and each ones seat was
          pointed out to him as ln a playhouee and each sat down to talk In
          whispers with his neighbors With their eyes upon the stage and its grue
          some 5ettgatbe chair with leathern straps and strange metal fittings
          they had not long to wait before the curtain was rung up
          The breaths of the witnesses could be heard at times as they sat there
          and waited The noise of the opening of a lock made a rasping sound be
          t hind the scenes and a catch came Into cacti ones throat There was the
          f round of shuffling feet on the cement floor outside the door of death Now
          L 1t was afthe threshold now Inside Some turned their heads to look most
          4 stared straight ahead at the chair
          WILLIS LED TO HIS DOOM
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024827/1912-08-11/ed-1/?sp=12&amp;q=Victims+Death+Chair+Execution+Electric+Executed+Electricity</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Aug. 10- Twenty-two
          jears ago this week, on August C,
          1890, William Kemmlcr, a condemned
          murderer, was put to death In the
          electric chair In Auburn prison. Kern.
          mler ttas the first victim to be legal
          ly executed by electricity in tb Unit
          ed States and his case was the sub
          ject of wide discussion at the time.
          The action of New York In substitut
          ing the electric chair for the gallows
          has been found generally satisfact
          ory and her example has been fol
          lowed by Ohio, Virginia, South Caro
          lina, Massachusetts, Kentucky auJ
          New Jersey.
          ijlnce the execution of Kemmler
          there hae been 151 persona put to
          death In the electric chair In New
          York. The state prison authorities
          estimate that It costs about J4000 per
          individual to carry, out the capital
          punishment mandate. On the basis
          of Oils estimate New York state haa
          expended about JC3.000 for electro
          cutions since that form of Inflicting
          the death penalty was introduced.
          Several times the electric chair at
          Sing Sing has had two victims in
          one day, and on one occasion a short
          time ago three persons were put to
          death within a period of twenty-four
          hours. Rut never before has there
          been such a wholesale execution of
          death sentences Imposed on prison
          ers In this state as is scheduled to
          take place at Sing Sing next week.
          Nino men are to die on the same
          day, and In as rapid succession H3
          they can be led to the death chair.
          -:ix of the nine prospective victims
          are the Italians who were convicted
          of the atrocious murder of Mrs Mary
          Hall at Croton Id Kit. Westchester
          County, on Nov 9, 1911.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86061215/1915-07-31/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Death+Electric+Chair+Electrocuted+Executed+Execution+Murdered+Rosenthal</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          BECKER IS EXECUTED
          WITH PRAYER ON LIPS
          (Continued From Page 1.)
          The one time police officer hesitated
          as he entered the execution room. It
          seemed to the witnesses as if he was
          startled that the death chair was so
          near at hand. He looked quickly at
          the double row of witnesses, glanced
          at the floor, swept with his eyes the
          whitened walls of the room and then,
          suddenly, as if coming to himself,
          walked briskly over the rubber mat
          and seated himself in the electric
          chair. Behind Becker followed the
          prison priests chanting the prayer of
          death, which was repeated by the con
          demned man.
          "Jesus, ijtfary, Joseph, hkve mercy on
          my soul," nervously spoke Becker as
          deputy wardens stepped forward and
          adjusted the electrodes. Hardly a
          minhte elapsed before the electrode
          was applied to the right leg, a slit
          having been previously cut in the
          trouser leg from the knee down. After
          the electrode had been firmly adjusted
          against a shaven spot on the back of
          the condemned man's head, the state
          executioner looked at Deputy Warden
          Johnson, who surveyed the figure that
          was ctlll mumbling the death prayer
          in the chair. Johnson half turned his
          head and the executioner jammed the
          switch.
          Three Shocks Given.
          The first shock lasted a full minute
          and the executioner said that it was
          1,850 volts and ten aniperes in
          strength. It came while Becker was
          still commending his soul to his
          niflknr.
          I The two prison physicians stepped
          forward to examine the collapsed flg
          ure that sat supported in the death
          chair by the thick black leather straps.
          The stethoscope was applied to the
          heart and Dr. Charles Farr, the prison
          physician, pressed his finger against
          the artery in the neck. There was
          still a feeble fluttering of the heart.'
          The physician stepped back from
          the rubber mat and again the electric
          current pulsed through the body. The
          shock lasted seven seconds and the
          current was then turned off. After 4
          hasty examination Dr. Farr asked that
          a third shock be given. This lasted
          nve seconds. An examination that
          took several minutes followed. Three
          physicians among the witnesses then
          made an examination and Dr.- Farr at
          5:55 o'clock proriounced Becker dead.
          Writes Last Statement.
          During the night Becker penciled on
          a piece of paper what he captioned
          "My Dying Declaration." It was tak
          en to the warden's office where two
          copies were typewritten, which Becker
          signed with his fountain pen in a bold
          hand To Deputy Warden Johnson,
          who bad charge of the execution in
          place of Warden Thomas Mott Os
          borne, who does not believe in the
          death penalty,
          Electric Chair Gets Men Who Murdered Rosenthal
          £L&amp;C7WC
          CHA/&amp;
          S/A/G vT/Att
          ik
          Lsrry lows
          which I must die. You are now about
          to witness my destruction by the state,
          which is organized to protect the lives
          of the innocent! May'Almighty God
          pardon everyone who has contributed
          In any degree to my untimely death.
          And now on the brink of my grave I
          declare to the world that I am proud
          to have been the husband of the pur
          est, noblest woman that ever lived—
          Helen Becker. This acknowledgment
          is the only legacy I can leave her. I
          bid you all good-bye. Father, 1 am
          ready to go. Amen/'
          (Signed) "Charles Becker."
          Talks All Night.
          After his wife had said farewell,
          shortly after midnight, Becker main
          tained a casual conversation with
          Deputy Warden Johnson who sat be
          side tne screen in front of his cell.
          Sometimes he smoked cigars, after
          jwhich he would let his head fall on
          I his hand and gaze reflectively at the
          I floor for minutes at a time. Dawn
          found him seated on the edge of his
          cot carefully pinning a photograph of
          his wife on his white shirt just over
          his heart. Then, as if he desired to
          have her all to himself, Becker put on
          a thin black alpaca coat, which he
          tightly buttoned. The photograph was
          not seen by the witnesses until the
          prison" physician opened his coat as he
          sat in the death chair.
          Becker was put to death by the state
          executioner whose name is unknown
          to the public. This man succeeded
          State Electrician Davis and he said he
          would not take the job unless his name
          wis kept secret. He lives in a little
          town up-state and went about his
          work briskly.
          Becker's executioner said that in his
          opinion the man had died instantly at
          the first contact.
          Negro Follows Becker.
          An autopsy on the body of Becker
          was performed, according to law, im
          mediately after the execution. After
          Becker's body had been removed from
          the electric chair, Samuel Haynes, a
          nefgro murderer, was brought into the
          execution room and electrocuted. One
          of Becker's last requests to Warden
          Osborne was that''he be put to death
          before Haynes.
          Mrs. Becker Makes Statement.
          A statement credited to Mrs. Becker
          was given out here shortly after her
          husband's death.
          TWO ELECTROCUTED
          IN KENTUCKY JAIL
          Eddyville, Ky., July 30—For the
          third time in the history of Kentucky
          a double electrocution took place this
          morning at 3:30 o'clock at the Eddy
          ville penintiary.
          The firBt to be executed was Turn
          er Graham, Jr., 24, a white man, con
          victed for the killing of R. J. Mc
          Murtry, sheriff of Hardin county. The
          second was William Lane, 25, a negro,
          convicted at Pineville, on a charge of
          killing his wife. Lane was the first
          negro to be executed in Kentucky
          since the adoption of electrocution as
          a means of inflicting the death pen
          alty. Both men passed the night
          calmly and walked unassisted to the
          death chamber.
          an ordinary human being—and per
          haps that Is why I loved him so."
          History of Case.
          Herman Rosenthal, the gambler for
          whose murder Charles Becker was sen
          tenced to die in the electric chair, was
          shot to death by hired gunmen in the
          early morning of July 16, 1912, in front
          of the Hotel Metropole on Forty-third
          street, a few stepB from Broadway.
          The murder was' the swift culmination
          of sensational charges made a few
          days before by Rosenthal against Beck
          er in which Rosenthal asserted that
          Becker, then head of the strong arm
          squad of detectives, freely sold police
          protection and had accumulated thou
          sands of dollars of graft money.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045389/1916-03-05/ed-1/?sp=48&amp;q=Die+Death+Electric+Chair+Electrocution+Electricity</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Scientists Have Just Discovered
          Many Secrets Which Have Long
          Puzzled Them in Regard to Death
          by Electric Shock From the Exper
          ience of a Man Who Was Electro
          cuted and Brought
          Back to Life
          WHKN the electric chair was sub
          stituted for the old fashioned
          gallows in New York it was be
          cause it was believed that electrocution
          was painless. But just what were the
          sensations of death in the electric chair
          scientists were unable to say, because
          no electrocuted victim came back to life
          to tell tliern.
          It was assumed that the shock of the
          powerful current would instantly render
          the condemned man unconscious. But
          the unpleasant feature of m^st electro
          cutions has been the necessity of re
          penting the shock several times. This
          was not foreseen
          Experience in ilie death chamber has
          shown that the electric current does
          not usually destroy life at the tirst shock.
          Evidences of pulsating life compel the
          executioner to turn on the current asain
          and yet again. This distressing failure
          of the electric charge to instantly end
          life has caused much speculation among
          scientists and humanitarians.
          Does the first shock end the conscious
          ness of the condemned man?
          Or is the victim siiil conscious?hover
          ing between death and life, does themau
          In the chair realize what is going on?
          What, if any, was the agony of the
          ti rs shock?
          What were the agonies of the victim
          during the moments elapsing between
          tiie tirst shock and the second impact of
          the current? Was he entirely uncon
          scious, partly conscious or fully conscious
          of the horrors of the situation which the
          law never meant to be inflicted on him?
          And if the tirst shock of the current
          benumbed the condemned man's brain,
          did returning consciousness bring with it
          tortures of bodily misery which have
          never been known or suspected?
          The Victim
          Falls Apparently Dead.
          Nobody has been able to answer these
          questions until an accident happened
          viiit-h unexpectedly illuminated this wholo
          subject of what the victim in the elec
          tric chair really sees, hears, foels and
          cu ffers.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83035682/1959-04-30/ed-1/?sp=13&amp;q=electric+chair</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038220/1947-04-07/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=electric+chair</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86090369/1911-11-24/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=death+chair</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          F. P. SMITH BEATTIE DIES IN
          ELECTRIC CHAIR
          Convicted Wile Murderer Elec
          trocuted After Acknowl
          edging His Guilt.
          NEVER LOSTJIS NERVE
          Condemned Man Walked Calmly
          and Unshaken to the Death
          Chair—Executed Shortly
          Alter Daylight.
          j _
          Associated Press Special.
          J Richmond, Va., Nov. 14.—Henry
          Clay Beattie, Jr., wag electrocuted In
          I the death chamber of the state pent
          lentlary this morning at 7:2i
          o’clock. One minute after the shock
          he was pronounced dead by the at
          tending physicians.
          After the execution of Beattie It
          was learned that he confessed to the
          murder of his wife. Although the
          prison authorities who were present
          at the execution said that Beattie
          made no statements which might be
          construed as an admission of guilt.
          It was afterwards learned that he
          lert a written statement with his
          spiritual advisers In which he admit
          ted his guilt. This statement was
          given out by the family some time
          after young Beattie's death.
          The confession of Beattie, which
          bore hla signature. Is aa follow*:
          “I, Henry Clay Beattie, Jr., desir
          ous of standing right before Ood and
          man, do on this the twenty-third day
          of November, confess my guilt of
          the crime against me. Much that has
          been published concerning the de
          tails was not true, but the awful
          fact without harrowing clrcumstau
          ces remain. For this action I am tru
          ly Borry, but believing that I am at
          peace with God and am soon to pa
          Into his presence, this statement Is
          made.”
          Beattie went to the death dealing
          chair unshaken and displaying the
          same remarkable nerve that charac
          terized him throughout the entire
          trial of his case and his subsequent
          fight to escape the chair.
          During his last night on earth
          Beattie slept well, but tossed rest
          lessly as though bad dreams had
          been his companions throughout the
          long time. There were no signs of a
          breakdown when he arose this morn
          ing, the prisoner dressing with the
          same fastidious care that he has
          taken ever since he entered the state
          penitentiary and the death cell.
          The death chamber Is undor
          ground and the only light waa above
          the death chair where It seemed to
          culminate with a ghastly glare and
          to leave the balance of th* room In
          almost total darkness. The twelve
          witnesses required by law wero
          ranged along the sides of th* cham
          ber back In this grewsome darkness.
          During the few momenta Beattie
          was a'lve after he entered the death
          chamber he saw nothing but the
          chair in which he was to be rtrapped
          to receive the deadly current.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1947-02-25/ed-1/?sp=26&amp;q=death+chair</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Sullivan Asked to Aid Youth
          Who Survived Death Chair
          By the Associated Press
          Gael Sullivan, executive director
          of the Democratic National Com-j
          mittee, said yesterday a group of i
          educators has asked his aid in seek
          ing executive clemency for Willie
          Francis, young Negro facing a sec
          ond trip to the electric chair in
          Louisiana.
          Mr. Sullivan told reporters he Is
          studying the case, but has taken no
          action and did not know what he
          might do. He discussed the matter
          when asked about reports that he
          would ask President Truman to
          commute Francis’ sentence.
          Francis, convicted of a holdup
          killing, went to the electric chair
          once but escaped death due to me
          chanical difficulties with the chair.
          His attorneys appealed to the Su
          preme Court to save him from a
          second trip to the chair, contending
          that would be cruel and unusual
          punishment barred by the Consti
          tution. The court split sharply on
          the question, but the majority held
          j Louisiana may legally attempt once
          j again to execute him.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1903-05-25/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=death+chair</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          HARDEST MAN IN
          WORLD TO KILL
          Slaying of Murderer Triola
          Proves the Greatest Task the
          Death Chair Has Ever Had to
          Perform
          The remarkable vitality of Antonio
          Trlolo put to death today tn SIng Sing
          prison for the murder of Maria Orolll
          the child actress proved him to toe the
          hardest man to kill that has aver been
          la th electric chair
          Triola was remarkably oool when led
          Into the death chamber He helped the
          attendants adjust the straps and elec
          tric appliances of the death chair It
          required five shocks of 1700 volts each
          the first four amperes and then eight
          for each of the other four times to
          kill the Italian No one In the prison
          had ever before seen INch difficulty
          at an execution
          Triola was very 0001 He roSe at tho
          first sign of dawn Other men con
          demned to die Including lawyer Al
          bert T Patrick and Arthur Flanagan
          who was to have met death today
          with Triola but was reprieved wer
          also up early
          An Hoar of Prayer
          When the ReT Fathers Mahoney and
          Martin called he knelt In prayer for an
          hour after receiving holy communion
          Shortly before 6 ocloclc the witnesses
          and State Electrician Davis gathered In
          the death chamber The apparatus of
          the death chair waa tested and found
          to bo In perfect condition
          Tho little procession then started
          from Trlolai cell The priests walked
          on one side of the condemned man
          hlUle time won lost In atrapplne the
          prisoner In the chair The signal was
          given and 1700 volts shot throurh the
          condemned mans body
          Dr Irvine Immediately MW that the
          man was not dead Again the current
          was turned on for thirty seconds but
          ngnlnlt failed although eight s
          ere used
          Onco more the current was shot
          through TrlolVa body but still he kept
          alive It was not until the fifth shock
          was given to him that life became ex
          tinct
        </text>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-eiffel-tower</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025121/1889-04-02/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+France+French+Paris+Worlds+Fair</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          THE EIFFEL TOWER
          A Msht and Sensation for lisitor to
          1arls
          In view of the assurance of a
          creditable representation of Hawaii
          both in productions and person
          agesat the Universal Exhibition of
          this year in Paris a few facts rela
          tive to the EiffeUower culled from
          a late English paper may be of local
          interest
          The tower is named after its pro
          jector Mr Eiffel now President of
          the French Association of Engineers
          He is famed in part -for the design
          ing of a great bridge at Bordeaux
          Although the Eiffel tower was orig
          inally the conception mainly of an
          ambition likened to that of Ameri
          cans by the English paper referred
          to for having the highest structure
          in the world it was also early as
          sumed that it would have uses in the
          interest of science It is claimed
          and anticipated that it will be very
          raluable for observatory purposes
          owing to the perfect clearness of the
          air at its summit
          The tower is to be one thousand
          feet in height At the date of the
          description here drawn upon it had
          attained an altitude of 738 feet or
          162 feet higher than any other build
          ing on earth There were 180 men
          employed then in its construction
          100 preparing the lifts at the base
          and 80 riveting the perfectly fitted
          parts at top To avoid fatiguing the
          workmen aloft in descending several
          times a day for food a restaurant is
          fitted up at a height of about 400
          feet There are to bo four perman
          ent restaurants for the refreshment
          of visitors on the first stage of the
          tower
          A spiral stairway runs from the
          ground to the summit of the tower
          but it is believed that few if any in
          experienced heads will be able to en
          dure the strain of going round and
          round or looking down from the
          giddy heights Therefore there are
          to be mechanical lifts to the top
          four to the first stage two to the
          second and thence one to the sum
          mit the crown of observation The
          final lift will have a capacity of 65
          persons I1 ares will be 6 francs to
          the first stage and 5 francs to the
          top to be reduced on Sundays to 1
          franc and 3 francs respectively No
          visitors are allowed during construc
          tion except on Sundays owing to
          danger of accident from a hammer
          or bolt falling from aloft Mr iffol
          pays a weekly visit to thoworks The
          workmeu have to endure severe cold
          at the summit whore the thermome
          ter sometimes registers several de
          grees below zero
          The panoramic view to be obtained
          of the beautiful city of Paris and
          environs froin the top of the Eiffel
          tower must be loft to the readers
          imagination until assisted by ac
          counts from the Hawaiian Commis
          sioners Col Spalding and Hon J
          A Cummins or unofficial visitors
          from these isies or descriptive writ
          ers in the foreign press after ex
          periencing the sensations of the
          sublime ascension and prospect
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn91068084/1889-04-26/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+Paris+Exhibition+1000+Feet+High+France+French+Worlds+Fair</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          NEARLY 1000 FEET HIG&amp;
          The Great Eiffel Tower at the
          Paris Exposition.
          How the Colossal Structure, Just
          Completed, was Erected.
          The great Eiffel tower at the Paris Exhi
          bition has just been completed, and a de
          scription of the colossal structure, with an
          account of the way it was built, and a sketch
          of its constructor, will bo appropriate at this
          time. It is scarcely necessary to say that the
          U
          mm

          Cologne
          Cathedral,
          511 ft.
          The Eiffel Tower,
          9S4 ft. The Great
          Pyramid,
          480 ft.
          Eiffel tower is by far the highest structure in
          the world. It presents a decidedly unique ap
          pearance, too in general outline not unlike a
          stack of four gigantic muskets with their
          butts well and solidly spread and their bay
          onets joining at their tips.
          The Eiffel tower stands in the Champ de
          Mars, almost on the left bank of the river
          Seine, just in the rear of the Quai d'Orsay,
          and in fact a part of its foundation is sunk
          through an old arm of the river, which lias
          been filled in these many years. Its base
          covers a plot of ground 328 feet square, or
          nearly two and a half acres in extent.
          GUSTAVF. EIFFEL.
          It Ls really at the base a group of four tow
          ers, each nearly fifty feet square, placed at
          the corners of the plot of ground, and in
          clining toward each other as they rise at an
          angle of fifty-four degrees. Each tower con
          sists of four columns, bound together by
          trusswork, and each column rests on a
          masonry pier which is so built that the weight
          of the column rests upon it squarely and not
          at an ancle.
          As the tower is 0S4 feet high. it will be
          seen that the matter of providing a solid
          foundation was one of great importance.
          There was a lot of boring and digging befon
          the spot upon which the tower stands was
          finally selected.
          The foundation rests upon a thick stratum
          of sand and gravel. It may be well to say.
          for the benefit of those who think sand is a
          rather treacherous sort f ground, that a bed
          of sand and gravel, away under ground, is
          pretty solid stuff. One of the towers of the
          Brooklyn Bridge rests on that sort of base.
          The foundations of the two piers of the Eiffel
          tower farthest from the Seine rest on sand
          and gravel about twenty-five feet below the
          surface of the ground. These foundations
          were laid in open excavations, and consist
          first of great solid platforms of beton, six
          feet thick, and next of four stone piers which
          rise to the surface to receive the iron col
          umns. The foundations for the two piers nearest
          the river were not so easily laid. It was
          necessary to go thirty-five feet below the
          surface of the ground, end this was sixteen
          feet under water. So caissons had to be
          used, as they were in building the Brooklyn
          Bridge piers.
          A caisson is in effect simply an enormous
          iron box, without any cover, turned upside
          down. The method of using it is to dig the
          earth out from under it and allow it to
          gradually settle as the excavation pro
          gresses, meanwhile building the pier on top.
          When the required depth is reached the cais
          a .n itself is filled up with the beton, and it
          forms the bottom layer of it a foundation.
          A shaft is left running through the pier
          auove for entrance and exit as the work goes
          on, and the air in the caisson and shaft is
          compressed to whatever is necessary to keep
          the water out of the bottom. It is the prin
          ciple of the diving bell modified.
          Work on the foundations was begun on
          January 28, 1887, and at the end of June they
          were completed. Then began the labor of
          setting up the innumerable pieces of iron of
          which the tower is composed, and it went on
          at a vapid rate, for each individual piece
          came from the works of M. Eiffel, at Leval-lois-Pere
          cut to its exact dimensions, fitted
          and drilled, so that no modification was neces
          sary at the place of operations. Up to a
          height of about fifty feet the workmen re
          quired no scaffolding to work upon, as each
          pier supported itself, although each leaned
          toward the others. Then an artificial support
          had to le provided, as above that height, un
          til the first platform was reached, the center
          of gravity of each pier would fall outside of
          the base.
          And so piece by piece the towers grew,
          and at length reached a height of 140 feet.
          Then four enormous horizontal trusses were
          put in place to connect the four piers. These
          were nearly 140 feet long and weighed a
          good many tons, and hi order to place them
          in position it was necessary to erect an ex
          tensive false work, or scaffolding. "When
          these trusses were in position, and the con
          necting beams to form a flooring were in
          place, the workmen ha1 a great solid plat
          form, nearly 15U feet above the ground and
          upward of 1 oJ feet square, to work upon.
          These four inclined piers and the four big
          connecting trusses form the solid groundwork
          of the tower. There is nothing particularly
          unique in the detail of construction. The
          work is simply a system of trusses and braces,
          in which the material is so placwd as to make
          a strong and light structure. The four great
          arches which rise between the piers, imme
          diately under the great horizontal trusses,
          are largely ornamental in character. They
          serve to round off what would otherwise be
          an angular outline, but do not support any of
          the weight of the structure.
          Above the lower platform two four-corner
          piers incline toward each other at a
          sharper angle. The iron columns are lighter
          and the spaces in the system of bracing are
          larger. High above the first platform, nearly
          400 feet from the ground, a second series of
          horizontal trusses binds the four piers to
          gether and forms the basis for a second land
          ing. These two platforms are glorious places
          St. Peter's,
          433 ft. Rouen
          Cathedral,
          470 ft.
          Statue of Wash- Column
          Liberty, ington Vendome,
          301 ft. Monument, 148 ft.
          500 ft.
          from which to view the city of Paris. They
          are so large that even very timid persons
          standing on them will lose all fear. The
          lower one is nearly half an acre in extent
          while the upper one is about one-third that
          size. From the platform a view of the coun
          try for forty miles around may be obtained.
          Above the second platform the four corner
          piers gradually approach each other and at
          length unite in one pier, at the top of which,
          nearty a fifth of a mile from the ground,
          there is a covered observatory, and above
          this rises a slender mast. Doubtless many
          thousand people will see Paris and ever so many
          square miles of surrounding country from the
          observatory during the summer. They will
          not have to walk up, for a gigantic elevator
          runs up through one of the piers to the very
          top. This elevator is of peculiar construction,
          for the carriage or truck, travels upward on
          a spiral track, while the car itself rises
          vertically, or rather as nearly vertically as
          the angle of the pier will allow.
          While the Eiffel tower was a stupendous
          conception, and will stand as completed
          the marvel of modern engineering, no new
          principles are involved in its construction.
          In fact, to an engineer, the most wonderful
          thing about the tower is its simplicity. The
          way for the Eiffel tower, both in conception
          and execution, was paved, after a fashion,
          by the work on the Garobit viaduct and the
          Taraes bridge, both of which were built by
          Eiffel. In fact, the construction of bridges
          and viaducts, without the use of scaffolding or
          false work, by making the several parts
          balance themselves as the work progresses,
          owes much to this French engineer.
          Gustavo Eiffel is a master of construction.
          It is said of him that he combines within
          himself the practical knowledge of the Eng
          lish engineer, the audacity of the American
          and the science and theories of the French
          man. He was born at Dijon, France, in 1S32,
          and was educated at the Central School of
          Sciences and Arts. He it was who first made
          practical use of compressed ah in cassions in
          the building of bridge foundations, in the
          erection of the great bridge at Bordeaux.
          TOP OF THE TOWER.
          M. Eiffel has been a busy man, indeed, these
          many years, but he found time, when the
          statue of Liberty Enlightening the World was
          to be set up in New ork Harbor, to design
          the skeleton framework which support the
          gigantic figure and at the same time firmly
          holds it to the granite pier on which it stands.
          A glance at the illustration will show to
          what extent the Eiffel tower overshadows all
          the famous tall structures of the world. In
          comparison with its 984 feet Cheops is dwarfed
          at 40. The Washington Monument is little
          less than 500 feet high, and the point of .he
          flame of Liberty's torch in New- York Harbor
          rises barely 300 feet in the air.
          The fees for ascending the Eiffel tower are
          five francs (1) to the cop, three francs
          (sixty cents) to the second platform an 1 two
          francs (forty cents) t. the first. The three
          platforms will hold 10,900 people.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87060190/1889-05-07/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+Paris+France+French+Expo+Exhibition+Worlds+Fair</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          At tho ontranco, spanning the gateway
          witu the vast archways of Ite base, rises tho
          gigantic Eiffel tower, 'MO metres high. Pass
          ing underneath it tho Central gardou is
          i cached. This has a monumental fountain
          BASE OF EIFFEL TOWER,
          ia tho middlo, and is surrounded by build
          ings containing exhibitions of flue arts,
          boUos lettres, tho liberal arts, and various
          departments of industry.
          Those buildings stand on parallel lines and
          ore crossed in their axis by a high gallery
          manaounted by a doma which leads to th
          hatt of machinery. Tho cost of tho build
          ings in tho Champs do Mars, exclusivo of tho
          Mffel tower, has been about (4,000,000, and
          it is intended that they shall remain as per
          aaaent structures. The total outlay author
          ised for tho entire exposition U 38,600,000, of
          wttch $000,000 is hold aa a rcerve fund.
          The earthworks required a removal of
          700,000 cubic foot. Tke drains and water
          pipes of the Camps do Mars were lengthened
          hf about two miles, and more than 40,009
          ems of iron and steel wero u&amp;ed by the
          holders. The hall of machinery is 1,309 feet
          long and 150 feet high, covered with a roof
          f iron, wood and glass, having a span of
          380 feet in tho clear, the greatest ever at
          tempted. A gullory extends around tke in
          terior for the display of tho lighter classes of
          machinery and from end to end run four un
          ferofcen linos of shafting for distributing the
          Beotivo power. Tho powor is dorived from a
          proup of steam engines placed in one of
          the touts, tho bollors of which transform
          into steam forty tons of wator per hour.
          The total energy is about 400 horse power.
          TJio chief architectural feature of the ex
          position is, of course, tho Eiffel tower, as
          wore the Crystal Palace at London In 1851,
          the iron lighthouse at Paris in 1807, tho groat
          THE EIFFEL TOWZ&amp; VBOX THE BEINK
          rotunda at Vionna in 1873, and the Trocadero
          palace at Paris in 1878. This is the loftiest
          structure eyer rahedjjy Iman, being about
          064 feet high. The Washington monumont
          now stands second, 55.5 feet. The Cologno
          cathedral is 501 feot. Tho tower of Babol
          was probably CS0 high. Moro than 7,000
          tons of metal were us?d in building tho
          Eiffel tower. Tho first sod was turned in
          excavation for its foundation on January
          28, 1887, and the whole work was completed
          on March 31, 1889.
          Another interesting feature is found in
          the gardens. Hitherto in tho Champs de
          Mars the visitor saw only a dusty desert.
          Now every bit not covered with buildings is
          a charming park with tho greenest of lawns,
          flourished, Minded paths, masses of shrub-
          bery. Moro than two years ago, before any
          of tho work of buildina was begun. M.
          Alphand, tho dirootor of public works, com
          pleted his plans, and traced on tho ground a
          detailed map of the garden trees. Shrubs
          were then plantod and seeds laid, and now
          the whole expanso looks liko a well-kept
          park of many years standing. Indeed, the
          abundance of vegetation on tho streets and
          squares is one of the most striking charac
          teristics of all Paris.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85033162/1900-05-18/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Paris+Exposition</id>
        <rel>0</rel>

      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032018/1894-01-31/ed-1/?sp=15&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+Paris+France+French+Worlds+Fair+1900+Exhibition</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Our rulers are greatly
          bored about the Eiffel tower; but as
          the concession was granted for twenty
          years it has got to stand; but the arch
          itects say consolingly that the 7 will
          try and hide it as much as possible.
          The sight of it vexes poetio souls,
          and Francois Coppee, the author, who
          is, by way of being, sthetio, wrote
          a formal protest to the government at
          the time of its erection to request that
          the plan should not be carried out on
          the ground that the Eiffel tower, being
          ugly and ungainly, and furthermore
          being visible from his windows, inter
          fered with his flow of inspiration.
          However, the tower was built never
          theless, and, although we are deadly
          tired of seeing it about, Coppee con
          tinues to write, so evidently his flow
          ol inspiration was only impeded and
          not permanently plugged up. Further
          more, we are to have a branch exhibit
          at Versailles, which will rouse that
          sleepy little town from its chief ou
          pation of listening to the grass grow
          ing in the streets. In the splendid
          park of Versailles, on either side of
          the grand canal, is to be the retro
          spective history of gardens throughout
          the ages.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83040198/1899-02-03/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+France+French+Paris+Exhibition+Worlds+Fair+Ladder+Clouds</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          A LADDER FROM THE CLOUDS
          Bach Will Be the Appearance of the
          Eiffel Tower of Parts When
          Painted.
          The Eiffel tower, say the gentlemen
          of esthetic temperament, must go.
          The Eiffel tower, say the gentlemen
          who know the law, must stay for some
          years yet. The Eiffel tower, say the
          esthetes. Is ugly, discouraging to the
          eye and an all-round nightmare. "Scaf
          fold I cries the carper. "Down with it
          It has no place in esthetic Paris,"
          "Impossible! objects the law. "When
          the company took a lease of it they
          got it for a term of 20 years.. You
          can't break the lease, and the time is
          nowhere up.
          "But, urges the esthete, "look at
          the shape, look at the size, look at the
          color! Is not the whole thing hideous"?
          If we can't destroy it we can at least
          improve it and lessen the offense to
          our senses."
          And so the Eiffel tower is going to be
          metamorphosed. It has. been in color
          a reddish brown, and it is the color to
          which the gentlemen with the fine ideas
          have long objected. They have called
          the tower a shameless creation and re
          peatedly ridiculed the commonplace
          tone of hue. And now they have pre
          v ailed, and the lower is going to be a
          thing of beauty, so far as that goes.
          Silver white is the color agreed upon,
          and it is urged that when the army of
          workmen have finished their painting
          the huge structure will look really not
          so bad after all. Ilalf a hundred men
          will be employed on the building, work
          ing hard every day for two months.
          And 50,000 kilogrammes of paint will
          be used up before the Eiffel tower has
          finally lost its brickdust coat and finds
          itself arrayed in the poetic covering
          which the esthetes have advised. Two
          coats of paint will be applied and the
          brushes will be busy.
          It has been objected that the tbwer
          has always had the appearance or hav
          ing been cast up in inartistic form by
          a careless earth. The tower has seemed
          to rise awkwardly from the ground,
          the critical have said. Why not give
          it such an arrangement as would sug
          gest the idea of dropping from the
          clouds? That would be a pleasing fan
          cy, and if the huge tower were lighted
          at regular intervals it would present a
          picture as of a brilliant creature of the
          clouds, and all the world would be lost
          in admiration. These plans were sug
          gested when the exposition of 1900 were
          tinder discussion, and they have been
          adopted. A ladder from the clouds.
          That was tbe idea. 'And with that the
          esthetic taste, was forced to be sat
          isfied.
          The Eiffel tower has long been the
          universal bed lamp of Paris. The great
          candle in the top would be sadly miss-d,
          even by those who have fought agair.&amp;t
          the continuance of the structure. That
          ever-swaying lantern is one of the won
          ders of the French capital. Y. Her
          aid.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1900-05-20/ed-1/?sp=43&amp;q=Feet+Tower+Eiffel+Paris+France+French+Worlds+Fair+Exhibition</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          AT THE FEET OF THE TOWER.
          FOREIGN PAVILIONS CLUSTERED AWAY
          FROM THE BUB DBS NATIONS.
          Round about the hus^ ff&gt;.-tf f&gt; .-t of the EfTei Tower
          will be found the pavilions of I antrtefl
          which lid not find a place in the Rue dcs Xa
          tions—the Swiss chalet, built completely of wood,
          surrounded with balconies and terraces, like the
          great Alpine chalets. It is not an official pa
          vilion for receptions, but a meeting place for
          the Swiss visiting Paris; the pavilion of San
          Marino, the little republic dovetailed into the
          kingdom of Italy, containing cereals, wine, oil,
          honey, lace, embroidery, pictures, furniture, uni
          forms and various works of art highly creditable
          to a country of only five thousand inhabitants;
          the pavilion of Siam adds its Oriental stamp to
          the peculiar architectural icedoin
          &lt; Morocco
          is divided into two distinct arts the Imperial
          Pavilion and the annexes, containing restau
          rant, cafes and shops. The Imperial Pavilion is
          a reproduction of one of the imperial kiosks of
          the ancient Fez palaces, erected by the side of a
          Tetuan minaret. Picturesque paintings in warm
          colors impart lite an African Orientalism to
          the general quaintness of the buildings. Then
          near the Woman Palace is the Pavilion of the
          Equator, a two storied building in Louis XV
          style. A tower surmounted by a cupola crowns
          the edifice, the whole of which, after the fair is
          over, will be taken down and sent to Guayaquil
          to serve as the town library. The interior, fur
          nished with Louis XV furniture, contains the
          chief products of the Republic of the Equator,
          such as fruits cacao, coffee, rubber, sarsaparil
          las, quinine, tobacco, vegetable ivory minerals
          and splendid woods; sugar, carpets, stuffs, lace,
          embroidery, palm fibre, and the plaited straw
          hats so well known as Panama hats.
          Among the many constructions clustered here
          mention must be made of the French Alpine
          Club, containing botanical and geological collec
          tions and exhibits of the best mountaineering
          necessaries, besides a panorama of the Alps and
          excellent photographs of the scenery; the Auto
          mobile Club; the Touring Club, open to all its
          members; the Chateau Tyrolian; a pavilion for
          exhibits of Russian alcohols; one for the history
          of ceramic art; branch buildings for business
          purposes of the three great banking establish
          ments Credit Lyonnais Society Generate and
          Comptoir d'Escompte and several high priced
          and fashionable restaurants
          Foreign Photos.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059523/1903-10-25/ed-1/?sp=24&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+Doomed+Rocks+Wind+Paris+France+French+Gustav</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          THE Eiffel Tower must come down.
          The authorities of Paris have so decreed.
          This iron spire, the tallest structure in the
          world, and the engineering feat of the last cen
          tury, \.i regarded as a dangerous plaything.
          When a high wind blows from the south the great
          ribbed structure trembles like a frightened horse.
          But let a stiff breeze come bowling down from the
          north and the tower vibrates until the china rattles in
          the cafes, and to those in the observatory at the apex the
          sensation is that of a ship fossed by heavy seas.
          The fact that the tower is more' sensitive to a wind
          from the north than from the south is regarded as proof
          of the structural weakness, and from this springs the
          theory of danger of collapse.
          It is almost twenty years since Gustav Eiffel began
          the work of building his sky-scraper. The mark of com
          pletion was set for 1889, Exposition year, and on March 31
          of that year the tower was thrown open to the public. It
          wa« the leading attraction of the big show, and it has
          not since ceased to attract attention and coin.
          The cost of building the structure was more than
          $1,000,000. Of that amount the French government appro
          priated $29L',000. Eiffel supplied the remainder, trusting
          for his reimbursement to the receipts from admission fees
          and other sources.
          In this he was not uisappolnted, as the profits of the
          first year were almost sufficient to make him whole.
          The lease held by Eiffel will expire in next March, and
          then, if the present plans of the city fathers are realized,
          the work of razing the unique structure will be started.
          The plan is to sell the tower to the highest bidder, the
          purchaser to be given a certain time in which to remove
          what Paris regards as almost a public menace.
          Except as a curio and an Investment for its builder,
          the tower has been somewhat of a failure.
          Much was expected in the scientific world from the
          metaphorical observatory, with its physical and biological
          laboratories, all 954 feet above ground. But little has
          come of this, the enterprise having taken on a rather
          commercial aspect.
          The Eiffel Tower will ever be considered a colossa*
          feat of engineering.
          PARIS, October 10.
          There are platforms at the 189, 380 and 906 feet levels,
          reached by elevators as well as by Btairs. Beyond the
          third platform a spiral staircase, which is not open to the
          public, ascends to the top of the tower.
          On the first platform, which has a floor space of 38,000
          Bquare feet, or nearly an acre, there were four restau
          rants at the time of the Exposition, and refreshments are
          Btill served there.
          The view from the top of the tower extends eight y
          flve miles on a clear day. At night a searchlight gleams
          from the eminence.
          Seven thousand tens of iron were used in building the
          Eiffel Tower.
          Gustav Eiffel made a long leap over precedent when
          he planned and built the spiral skeleton of Iron which
          made him rich and famous.
          The ambition of the Egyptians to pierce the sky with
          pyramids carried them less than half as high as this
          French engineer went on a comparatively fragile founda
          tion.
          The pyramid of Cheops 13 only 486 feet high; that of
          Cephrenes 456 feet.
          The best that Rome can do, with all her boasted
          achievements in lofty architecture, is to point to the dome
          of St. Peter' s—a paltry 448 feet above ground.
          London steps into third place in these Old World ver
          tical achievements with her St. Pauls dome—36s feet up.
          Campanile, the famous leaning tower at Pisa, did not
          win fame because of the height of its arcaded colonnades
          bo much as because of its obliquity, and yet when we are
          told that this tower is thirteen feet out of plumb we
          learn in the same breath that it is 179 feet high!
          Stepping over to the New World to complete the table
          of comparisons more ambitious figures are encountered,
          and yet our best achievements are as pigmies in the
          shadow of the tower that Eiffel built.
          The Eiffel Tower possesses the sole distinction of altl
          tude. Barren of other claims upon the public attention,
          the need of outstripping—virtually doubling—the elevation
          of any other tall structure is apparent.
          Scattered over.lreland and Scotland, or,Jiere %nd there
          on the Islands of Corsica and Sardinia, are to be found
          the ruins of some of the towers of prehistoric times.
          These, like those of our cathedrals .and public build
          ings of to-day, were built for purposes of utility.
          The old round towers ot Ireland, as well tta the
          "brochsT of Scotland, were used as places of refuge or
          defense in time of war, as wateff towers and as resort for
          the recluse.
          The architecture was at first plain and severe, while
          In later years appeared parapets and pinnacles richly
          canopied.
          These towers were never mbfe than 132 feet high, with
          the average perhaps 80 feet.
          In remote times the Moslems' built towers of stone
          that they used as minarets. The finest of these belong
          to the thirteenth, century, notably the Mlnan of Kootub,
          at Old Delhi, which was the wjonder of ail the tribes that
          gathered about it.' This towei^ was 250 feet high, built of
          massive blocks of limestone and marble.
          Not since the days of Babel, if, indeed, before, has the
          building of a tower for the mere pride of building it been
          essayed. Confusion of tongues Svas the result then.
          Coming down to the age «f a*»ial playthings, modern
          ingenuity seems to have spelled for itself a lesson—one
          less severe than that of Babel, bat, nevertheless, a lesson.
          Having ventured past the point of practicability and
          safety, the monument erected'by Gustav Eiffel to tho
          genius and daring of man faHa; before the force of the
          elements, while the dust of ages-icontlnues to settle upon
          the sloping sides of the pyramids.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1907-03-10/ed-1/?sp=47&amp;q=Eiffel+Tower+Gustav+Paris+France+French+Republic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          j GIGANTIC war wareye wareye
          eye that th a twill twillsweep will willsweep
          sweep the whole of ofFrance ofPranceher
          France Pranceher her fron frontiers fro1Zjers
          tiers jers her chains clzaillsof clzaillsoffortresses of offortresses
          fortresses and her herseaboard herscaboardsllch
          seaboard scaboardsllch such Is Isto isto
          to be the I further furthermission furthermisJion
          mission of Ithc the fa famous famOlls
          mOlls Eiffel Tower Toweri Towerof
          i of Paris ParisThis Par J JThis
          This struct strllcillrc strllcillrcere lire
          4 e ere r e c t c d a as s the thechief thechief
          chief curiosity of ofthe ofthe
          the Paris Exposi Exposition E 4posi 4position
          tion has outlived outlivedits
          its 11 usefulness in other respects and has hasbeen hasbeen
          been made the central point of the great greatwireless greatwireless
          wireless signal system of the French army armyand armyand
          and navy
          From the top of the tower which is
          984 feet from the ground roll1td officials of the thearmy thearmy
          army may direct military operations op ratio1Zs in any anyLift allYLftt
          Lift up your eyes and behold them that come from fromthe tromthe
          the NorthJer aclll 0 0URLNG 0D
          FlUNG the army manoeuvres last fall fallthe fallthe
          D the various corps were directed from fromthe fromthe
          the now station Later fleet movements movementsin mO mcnts mcntsin
          in the Englislrchannel El lis1 chRnnel and the Mediter Mediterranean M diter diterranean
          ranean wore ordered ord 6dwithout without a hitch in the samo samoway sarnotvaJr
          way wayQuite Quite lecently the scope scoP of communication communicationfirm
          comunicatio1f
          firm f m the tower towmlms has been Cxf rlendc1 ended so that no nOtY nOtYmessages v
          vmessages.
          Should France and England become becomeallies becolleallies
          allies in some future conflict direct com communication commtl1licat
          mtl1licat munication on with London can be maintained maintainedfrom mailltailledfrom
          from the Eiffel Tower Southward from fromit
          it waves of warning anJtSfypmmand Jm1lZmzd will willfloat j
          float into d Algeria 19cria and Tunis From this rc rcmarkable rcmarkable
          markable tower may issue orders that wilt wiltchange willdt willdtczange
          change the 7i of Europe v vfel
          czange map ap i iI iI iIel I I
          fel the tower was completed in March 1889 lSS9jn lSS9jntime in intime
          time to tOSCITe serve as 13 one of the notable features featur 5J of ofthe oftlte
          the exposition of that year ear It was the loading loadingattraction leallingattraction
          attraction of that big show and has never neversince neversinceceased since sinceceased
          ceased to draw visitors and coin coinIt coinIt
          It cost considerably over 1000000 to build buildtho buildtho
          tho tower for which 7000 tons of metal were wereused wereused
          used Of the cost 292000 was voted by tha thagovernment thlgovernmont
          government while the engineer supplied the therest thereat
          rest The profits for 1SS9 alone nearly paid nid tha thacost thacost
          cost
          Some idea of its height height984 984 fcot feotway niay be begained begained
          gained from a comparison with other structures structuresof
          of the world Tho Washington Monument at atWashington atVashington
          Washington D C is 555 feet tall the broad broadbrimmed broadbrimmed
          brimmed hat of William Penn on Philadel Philadelphias Philadelphias
          phias City Hall is 547 feet above the pave pavement pavement
          ment the dome of St Peters in Rome rises risesto risesto
          to only 448 feet while the great pyramid of ofCheops ofCheops
          Cheops is but 486 feet high highFrom highFrom
          From the top of the Eiffel Tower on onjlclear onjlclearday tclear tclearday
          day one can see about eightyfive mUei At Atnight Atni
          night ni ht a searchlight from this eminence stabs the thesurrounding thesurrounding
          surrounding darkness darknessAt darknessAt
          At its base this wonderful tower covers coversnearly coversnnarb
          nearly twc and a half acres of ground Its
          mt tmTf iY Wf Wflower
          lower section consists of four builtup iron col columns c ll llumns
          umns each of which consists of four smaller smallercolumns smaUercolumns
          columns resting on masonry piers piersSpringing piersSpringin
          Springing gracefully upward tho th four fourmain IOlrmain
          main columns curve toward each other until
          020 feet above the surface they join in si single singlecolumij singlecolum
          columij colum Above this the long needle of the thetower thetocr
          tower rises rie 3G4 feet higher higherAt1 higherAtlS0
          At1 AtlS0 ISO feet at 3SO feet and again a ain at 006 006feet 908feet
          feet there are platforms which are reached by byelevators byelevators
          elevators as well as by b stairs stairsFrom stairsFrom
          From the t e highest highcstplatform platform a winding stair stairway stairway
          way climbs to the very pinnacle of the struc structure strueture
          ture but this part has never been open to the thepublic theBublic
          public publicWhen
          When qen these different platforms are can canverted CQ CQverted
          verted in into tn airship stations the French will in indeed indeed
          deed possess pOSdc a novelty of which they may b bproud bproud
          proud proudThey They are daring enough to attempt almost almostanything am06tanything
          many England 1 11lalld or Italy they coUld be diraifced diraifcedby dire W Wby
          by the Eiffel Tower station far infc in those t coun countries e UIl UIltriesto
          tries triesto to the centals of England E Jnd ntd Geratmnv Geratmnvdid GerJBatydid
          did they succeed iu getting getti that fan fanBat farBut
          Bat if the main duty were defense of the therepublics therepublics
          republics home territory the wireless wirel s aerrice aerricewould 5er 5erwouJd
          would probably pro ftbJ be even better as more or less lesspermanent JesgpermaJKnt
          permanent stations could be erected V 10D iig the tbeline theJi
          line Ji e of frontier fr tDtier fortifications from which to tocommunicate toOOIDJDuuicate
          communicate with Eiffel EiffelWhen Ei eL eLmen
          When men the new frontier line was drawn d awn by byGermany oyGerman
          Germany German after the war of 1S70 it was so ar arranged arranged
          ranged that all the strongest positions should shouldmi ouJd ouJdthe
          mi the German side of the line France Franceof Fraooc1sof
          of defense stands stan s back from the theraiflaer te tetier
          tier igt t Verdun Toul Belfort and Bipan Bipancon san sanCOlt
          con conThe The defenses d fenses of Paris are fifty fiftymilsiay fiftymilsiayfrom milo
          xjiray xjirayfrom
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1907-05-18/ed-1/?sp=26&amp;q=Dangerous+Painting+World+Eiffel+Tower+Paris+France+French+Republic+Gustav</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          I MOST
          DANGERO1
          NEW COATS FOR
          The Trocadero m Seen Through the
          "Lege" of the Tower.
          Height of the Great Tower
          as Compared to Some of
          the World's Tallest
          Structures.
          Special Correspondence of The Star.
          PARIS, May A, 1907.
          A painter has Just fallen from the Eiffel
          Tower. Four more men must fall to make
          the awful average of the most dangerous
          painting Job in the world?repeated every
          six years only.
          They are repainting the Eiffel Tower,
          and all Paris is concerned about the color,
          on which depends whether the gigantic
          mass of iron shall be the eyesore or the
          glory of the capital.
          Its first shade was "dead leaf," In 1889.
          When the sun lit it up to hazy golden with
          an unreal effect of Jeweler's fragility, even
          the artists who now corse it admitted that
          the Eiffel Tower had its nobility.
          In 1896, after immense discussion, they
          repainted It orange, magnetic currents
          even more than light and weather having
          turned it to a dingy chocolate, heavy and
          obtrusive. In strong sun the orange
          showed gleaming copper or red gold. Oscar
          Wilde declared It magnificent. Puvis de
          Chavannes threatened to blow It up with
          dynamite. From this period dated the bad
          name the tower acquired as a colossal
          piece of engineering vulgarity, usurping
          the artistic note of Paris.
          Then, for the exposition, they painted it
          "sun color." In bright lights the tower
          became a thing of glory once again.
          "All Depends Upon the Faint."
          "All depends upon the paint!" declares
          the city's architect, Bouyard, "a fact
          which shows the utter inartistic character
          of the Titan 1^3 intruder. The pyramids ol
          Egypt were originally cased with gleaming
          marble; but its present lack does not
          detract from the artistic appropriateness
          of the pyramids to their situation!"
          The tower gleamed sun color seven years
          agoi But the atmospheric electricity received
          every hour since then by such an
          unprecedented mass of iron reaching into
          the air so high is Incalculable. Conducting
          tubes a foot and a half in diameter
          lead it down the four niles to flftv feet be
          low the water-bearing stratum; but the
          effect on the paint la there for every one
          to see. It does not crack the paint off.
          The paint simply disappears, leaving the
          ugly chocolate, the dingy brown of the
          oxidising iron.
          It Is the tower's way of "calling for new
          victims. Fifty painters, working continuously
          together, take three months to do a
          ingle coat Few tourists realise- the immense
          proportions of the tower, but
          Parisian!, by experience, show you a peculiar
          phenomenon of Its deceptive symmetry.
          They take you In a cab close to the
          tower. It looks heavy and chunky. It
          seems sinking into the earth from lU
          weight. Half a mile distant from that
          oab the tower grows higher and slenderer.
          It seems to lift Itself from the earth, like
          a person rising from his knees. "Why, It's
          bigger than before!" you say. At a mil*
          distant-It seems quite as near. The river
          boats ttmt flit beside It now look tiny. The
          buildings round about are growing small.
          But the tower grows! Then at two miles?
          from the heights above Passy?It appears
          A 4kin? A# litfhtnMa hl alAn^nrAf
          Efc IIIIUB Vi u fc?v? gutiUVBWi ?and
          more open In Its lacework than when
          you gaped at its foot almost disappointed!
          In a country town thirty miles from
          Paris I have sat at night and watched Its
          leaxchltsht!
          Some Comparisons.
          Tou think Niagara Falls are high? They
          are 105 feet, and St. Paul's Cathedral, Lon- 1
          don. is 404 feet. Niagara Falls could de
          scend from below St. Paul's dome. Now
          place St. Paul's beside the Eiffel tower. It
          reaches only to the second platform of the
          tower?the real beginning of its slender
          shaftl
          Place the Eiffel tower beside the greatest
          buildings of the world. The great pyramid
          does not reach to Its Intermediate platform.
          Neither does the spire of the Cologne 1
          Cathedral.
          Only one 'set of buildings, nevertheless,
          are higher than the Cologne Cathedral
          Bplre. They are the sky-scrapers of American
          dtles, the tallest actually existing being,
          say, 6S6 feet high. It would not reach to
          the tower's intermediate platform, either.
          The loftiest masonry construction In the
          world is to be the Singer building extension,
          at the corner of Liberty street and
          Broadway, New Torlc. Beating any other J i
          American sky-scraper by 57 feet, it will i
          stick 612 feet into the air. And yet even j
          It will not reach to the Eiffel tower's inter- i
          mediate platform 1
          You can easily detect this intermediate i
          platform half way up the slender shaft of 3
          the Eiffel tower. In the nearer photographs j
          It shows for what it is?a mere platform
          for styftlng passengers from one set of ele- t
          vators to another, built In the center of the 1
          the time you git left. This yere man. Bob
          Hampton, Is my prisoner, an' I'll take him
          to Cheyenne. If I have ter brain every tough t
          in Glencaid to do It. Thet's me, gents." 1
          "Oh, come oft; you can't run your notions j
          igin the whole blame moral sentiment of c
          this camp." c
          "Moral sentiment! I'm backln' up the t
          aw, not moral sentiment, ye cross-eyed c
          jeer-slinger, an' if ye try edgin' up ther l
          mother stfep I'll plug you with this '45.' c
          There was a minute or hesitancy while i
          iie men below conferred, the marshal f
          ooking contemptuously down upon them, c
          lis revolver gleaming ominously in the v
          lght. Evidently the group hated to go back
          without the prisoner. j
          "Oh, come on. Buck, show a little hoss i&lt;
          fense." the leader sang out "We've got c
          &gt;very feller in camp along with us, an' 1
          :here ain't no show fer the two o' ye to t
          lold out against that sort of an outfit." 8
          Mason smiled and patted the barrel of hia
          -olt-
          "Oh. go to biases! wnen i want any aa- t
          rice, Jimmie, I'U send fer ye."
          Some one flred, the ball. digging up the f
          10ft earth at the marshal's feet, and fling-
          ng it in a blinding cloud into Hampton's f
          &gt;yes. Mason's answer was a sudden fusi-
          ade. which sent the crowd flying helter- 8
          skelter into the underbrush. One among
          hem staggered and half fell, yet succeeded
          Wmcelf nnt nf slffht V
          "Great Scott, If I don't believe I winged
          Fanjes!" the shooter remarked cheerfully,
          -eaching back Into his pocket for more f
          cartridges. "Maybe them boys will be a
          )lt more keerful If they once onderstand v
          hey're up agin the real thing. Well, per-
          laps I better skin down, fer I reckon It's
          table ter be rifles next" t
          It was rifles next, and the "wincing" of
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 5 Extra documents -->
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045499/1938-09-19/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=paris+tower</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Eiffe! Tower
          Flat for Rent
          PARIS, Sept. 19. Apartment for
          l-ent. Apply, Monsieur Marc, Eiffel
          Tower, Paris.
          Perched more than 1,000 feet
          above the ground on the third
          platform of the Eiffel Tower here,
          a little penthouse flat is for rent.
          It is very small—just one room,
          bathroom and kitchen—»nd one of
          steel structure passes through the
          floor and ceiling of the living room.
          But it is unique in the world. Its
          view is incomparable.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014519/1928-03-10/ed-1/?sp=12&amp;q=paris+tower&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.242,-0.074,1.484,1.484,0</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87062169/1925-06-27/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=paris+tower</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          WILL USE EIFFEL TOWER
          PARIS, June 27 (JP)—The govern
          ment today authorized Andre Citroon
          the Henry Ford of France, to rent the
          Eiffel tower for electric sign adver
          tisements.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016655/1889-10-05/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=eiffel&amp;r=-0.282,-0.255,1.564,2.032,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          The Eiffel Tower.
          The Eiffel tower is getting decidedly
          what may be called “aggravating.” Do
          what you will, you cannot get rid of it
          —wherever you go, there it is staring
          vou in the face. If you try to turn your
          back upon it, all along the boulevards
          and the principal streets are Eiffel tow
          ers of every size, devoted to every pur
          pose, from tiny charms for watch chains
          to large clocks for halls. If you fly to
          the country around Paris, there it is
          at every turn, looming down from the
          clouds—a nightmare cobweb, hanging in
          the skies. If your horizon is bounded
          by tiny suburban gardens, there again
          are miniature Eiffel towers, with little
          flags on the top, in exasperatingly bad
          taste. If a tall woman goes down a
          street, the gamins run after her shout
          ing: “Mme. Eiffel! Mme. Eiffel!” And,
          of course, the high notes of the new so
          prano, Mme. Melba, soaring into the
          skies up to G in alt, are called “des
          notes Eiffel." Oh! who will deliver us
          from the Eiffel tower! But there it is,
          and one cannot help looking at it; and
          there are the people swarming like in
          sects in what seems a mere piece of iron
          network; and there are the lifts, in sem
          blance of small white houses, clinging
          to the girders like caterpillars on a wall,
          crawling upward and downward.—Mur
          ray’s Magazine.
          As a Business Ventar*.
          The business of the Eiffel tower turns
          out to be immense. M. Eiffel calculated
          that when everything was in working
          order the gate money would be SS,OOO a
          day. Since the lifts have been in opera*
          tion he is thought to have averaged more
          than this. It costs a franc to enter the
          tower, two francs to get up in the lift to
          the second floor, and four francs to the
          top. On any of the ordinary full price
          days more than 20,000 people have paid
          admission, and with the increased prices
          for those using the elevator, the entire
          receipts exceed SIO,OOO. The original
          cost of the Eiffel tower, all included,
          was a little less than $1,000,000. The
          proprietor has to keep it in repair, and
          hand over one-fourth of his gate money
          to the exhibition. It is estimated that it
          will be half paid for when the exhibi
          tion closes, and then it will remain cer
          tainly three years more, and perhaps
          ten.—Boston Budget.The Eiffel Tower.
          The Eiffel tower is getting decidedly
          what may be called “aggravating.” Do
          what you will, you cannot get rid of it
          —wherever you go, there it is staring
          vou in the face. If you try to turn your
          back upon it, all along the boulevards
          and the principal streets are Eiffel tow
          ers of every size, devoted to every pur
          pose, from tiny charms for watch chains
          to large clocks for halls. If you fly to
          the country around Paris, there it is
          at every turn, looming down from the
          clouds—a nightmare cobweb, hanging in
          the skies. If your horizon is bounded
          by tiny suburban gardens, there again
          are miniature Eiffel towers, with little
          flags on the top, in exasperatingly bad
          taste. If a tall woman goes down a
          street, the gamins run after her shout
          ing: “Mme. Eiffel! Mme. Eiffel!” And,
          of course, the high notes of the new so
          prano, Mme. Melba, soaring into the
          skies up to G in alt, are called “des
          notes Eiffel." Oh! who will deliver us
          from the Eiffel tower! But there it is,
          and one cannot help looking at it; and
          there are the people swarming like in
          sects in what seems a mere piece of iron
          network; and there are the lifts, in sem
          blance of small white houses, clinging
          to the girders like caterpillars on a wall,
          crawling upward and downward.—Mur
          ray’s Magazine.
          As a Business Ventar*.
          The business of the Eiffel tower turns
          out to be immense. M. Eiffel calculated
          that when everything was in working
          order the gate money would be SS,OOO a
          day. Since the lifts have been in opera*
          tion he is thought to have averaged more
          than this. It costs a franc to enter the
          tower, two francs to get up in the lift to
          the second floor, and four francs to the
          top. On any of the ordinary full price
          days more than 20,000 people have paid
          admission, and with the increased prices
          for those using the elevator, the entire
          receipts exceed SIO,OOO. The original
          cost of the Eiffel tower, all included,
          was a little less than $1,000,000. The
          proprietor has to keep it in repair, and
          hand over one-fourth of his gate money
          to the exhibition. It is estimated that it
          will be half paid for when the exhibi
          tion closes, and then it will remain cer
          tainly three years more, and perhaps
          ten.—Boston Budget.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn91068084/1889-04-26/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=eiffel&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.338,-0.334,1.675,2.176,0</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          The range of observation from the top of
          the Eiffel Tower is forty miles.
        </text>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>

  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ouija-board</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84028296/1886-04-29/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch+Talking</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          THE NEW TALKING BOARD.
          Tfce
          MjitarlMS AaBaaeaaeat Which la
          raeelaattBt; Okls reettltk
          Many of our readers will still remember
          planchette, the strange little heart-shaped
          board with a pencil at its point which used
          to walk over yards of paper and write no and
          of tenie and nonsense if the finger tips of two
          persons touched the upper surface of the
          board.
          Planchetts had Ka day, and mostl died
          out But the same mysterious force which
          used to impel it it moving now another kind
          of little board, and setting whole eommuni
          Uet of eminently sober and respectable Ohio
          people on their heads.
          You see how it it made. A bit of board,
          say 18x30 inches, is lettered, rather large,
          with the alphabet, A, B, C, D, etc The
          letters are put a small distance apart At
          the upper corners of the board are written
          the words "yes" and "no," the "yes" on tha
          left, the "no" oa the right On tha left and
          right hand lower corners respectively are
          written "good evening and "good night
          Underneath tha letters of the alphabet are
          the figures in a row, the whole arranged like
          thit:
          t'esV no.
          j ABC OS VGH I JKL MIf
          ibPQBSTUVrVXVK.,
          1334T8V0 i
          Good-eve.
          Good-night
          Hen a tiny table it made with four legs.
          It is three or four inches high and very thin
          and light Two persons tit opposite each
          other and take the board upon their knees at
          in the picture. The little four-legged table ia
          placed upon the board. The two persons
          grasp tightly with the thumb and forefinger
          the comers of the table that are next to them.
          TBS TAXKXJfQ fJOABDb
          The two sit down and become quiet, asking
          rtioml" After a few minutes the little table
          begins to move over the board, It is an In
          tel lig nt, or at least, a semi-intelligent force
          that guides the table, for it answers
          questions. Bomettmes It talks utter nonsense
          and again it will write real information.
          The table spells out sentences in this way.
          When a question is asked, the table moves
          towards the tetters, and the foot stops upon
          the first one of the sentence to be written out
          Then it passes to the next one and the next
          and so on, with more or less rapidity, a
          gentleman, who hat experimented with the
          thing, says: "Sometime the table will cover
          two letters with Its feet and then yon hang
          on and ask that the foot be moved from the
          wrong letter, which will be done,"
          One man who tnougnt nit lamiiy was
          spending too much time over the talking ma
          chine burned it up. Then he left noma on a
          Journey. When the talking board could not
          be found some one made anotner, ana tne
          amusement went on. as before. To tho qu
          tion what had become of the other board the
          answer was given, "Jack burned It up,
          which somewhat astonished Jack on his re
          turn.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016373/1890-12-21/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=Mysterious+Talking+Wonder+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          "HE
          Nineteenth Century
          This most interesting and
          mysterious talking board has
          awakened great curiosity wher
          ever shown.
          It surpasses in its results
          second sight, mind reading, or
          clairvoyance.
          It consists of a small table
          placed upon a large board con
          taining the alphabet and nume
          rals. By simply resting the
          fingers of two persons upon
          the small table it moves, and
          to all intents and purposes be
          comes a living, sensible thing,
          giving intelligent answer to
          any questions that can be pro
          pounded. Wonderful as this may seem
          the "OUIJA" was thoroughly
          tested at the United States
          Patent Office before the patent
          was allowed.
          For sale by all first-class toy
          dealers and stationers.
          MANUFACTURED BY
          THE KEMARD NOVELTY m,
          220 SOUTH CHARLES ST.,
          BALTIMORE, MD.
          de21-lt,'i
          THE WASHINGTON
          Loan and Trust Co.
          Temporary Oillccs: Cor. 10th and
          F Streets N. W.
          Under Act of Coiiki-cbh Approved October
          1, 1890.
          Subject to supervision of tho Supremo Court of
          the District of Columbia and tho Comp
          troller of tho Currency.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn94052989/1893-11-14/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=Weird+Writings+Craze+Unseen+Forces+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          THE MORNING CALL, SAN FRANCISCO, TUESDAY, NOVEMBER 14, 18*3;'
          WEIRD WRITINGS.
          The Planchette Craze Has
          Broken Out Again.
          UNSEEN FORCES AT WORK.
          Some Uncanny Pranks of a Little
          Instrument That Once Held the
          Attention of the World.
          There Is a planchette fever in San Fran
          cisco.
          Clubs of patient sitters, anxious to hold
          communion with the dead and distant liv
          ing, have been formed here and in Oak
          land. Daily and nightly seances are being
          held.
          Plancbette is old, so old that it is almost
          new again. Early in the fifties the weird
          little contrivance was invented and ten
          years later nearly the whole civilized world
          was teaming with a recital of its wonders.
          The most uncanny tales were related of
          the marvelous doings of the instrument,
          and for a time the greatest scientific minds
          of the world were interested iv its queer
          pranks. Such men as Tyndall and Faraday
          were drawn Into controversies pro and con
          over the merits of this occult agency.
          Exhaustive essays were written and
          learned lectures delivered to prove that
          planchette was a fraud and to prove that
          planchette's powers were supernatural.
          But it all ended where it began. The
          deepest study and the most careful analy
          sis of the wiles and ways of planchette
          developed nothing of scientific value either
          to the student of the occult or the natural
          forces.
          And so the planchette fever died as
          quickly as it had grown. Men and women
          went back to their workaday world or con
          tinued their occult studies unuer different
          auspices. Planchette had it« little day nnd
          then died a natural death. Or, if it did not
          i die entirely, it lapsed into a slate of coma
          j from whicn it is only now being resur-
          I rected. To-day, in San Fraucisco aud in
          j Oakland, and perhaps In other parts of
          ihe world, great numbers of men and
          women are bent on solving the mysteries
          i that still cling to this little contrivance.
          And it is all because of that irrepressible
          j desire of man to penetrate the mysteries
          j of the future. f ,v
          What does to-morrow hold for me.
          That is the question nearest the heart of
          most men to-day. lt is a very part of the
          commercial spirit of the age. And as yet
          science has made no advances toward
          placing the means within reach of answer
          ing it. So planchette comes again to fill
          the gap between the known and the un
          known.
          What started the fever no one seems to
          i know. 'Hint it has been started and has
          already interested hundreds of intelligent
          men and women no one doubts, for the evi
          dence is clear.
          You know what planchette is, do you
          j not, and how it operates? Some have
          thought there was a hidden secret in its
          I construction, but this is wrong. Never
          was a wonderful device more simply con
          trived; There is first a heart-shaped cedar
          board. Pendant from the points of the
          angle are little legs with metal or wooden
          castors. At the end of the board is an
          aperture for the insertion of a lead pencil.
          Those who fit to planchette for communi
          cations from this world or the next place
          a baud each on the surface of the board,
          then wait till the "spirit moves." And
          the spirit has been moving pretty rapidly
          in these parts of the world for the last
          few nights. Dire things have been fore
          told and timely warnings given.
          Ordinarily planchette will write out
          what it has to say if time be given i\ but
          the quicker way is to write the alphabet
          and the simple negative and affirmative on
          a large sheet of white paper and let plan
          chette spell out its messages by pointing to
          tbe letters.
          It was this method pursued py a party
          of well-known clubmen who began as
          i skeptics Friday evening and went home at
          I daybreak firmly convinced that there were
          i at least many things that they had little
          j dreamed of In their phiiosophy. Only two
          members of the party placed tbeir hands
          on the instrument at one time. The others
          j looked on and scoffed.
          "We were all unbelievers when we sat
          down to that table," said the member of
          the party who told the story to a Call
          man yesterday. "For a while planchetie
          refused to move and we were almost on
          the point of giving it up for the night,
          when, without un Instant warning, the in
          strument gave a sudden jerk and almost
          flew from uuder the fingers of Jones and
          Smith.
          "Roth the men turned pale at this and
          in order to rally themselves they accused
          each other of having moved the planchette.
          On their honor both men denied this, but
          since neither had believed his own accusa
          tion the denials were useless.
          "I think it was a wife or a sister of
          Jones that came first. I bave forgotten
          the name of the spirit or influence, or
          whatever it was, that purported to move
          the instrument, but the information it im
          parted can be easily verified or disproved
          when the next news from Samoa arrives.
          "It spelled out 'Apia' first, very clearly
          and unhesitatingly. Then it went on to
          say that a terrible hurricane would sweep
          over the Samoan Islands on the 10th of
          November and that two vessels would be
          lost In the storm. And touching this
          event it would say no more, though we
          plied it with queries for a long time.
          "Another influence came. I remember
          tbe name, but shall not give it.
          'Dead or living?' asked Smith.
          'Living,' came the answer, but Smith
          knew this already, for the name it gave
          was the name of his sweetheart.
          'What have you to tell me?' queried
          Smith, and then he wished he had not,
          for the answer that came distressed bim
          sorely.
          "Twill not marry you,' it spelled out
          with painful accuracy.
          'Why not?', was the natural question
          that followed when Smith had recovered
          his presence of mind and bad determined
          to face it out.
          'Because I like D— letter,' came the
          answer.
          "Then two men glared at each other for
          a moment, for D— sat at the opposite end
          of the table waiting bis turn to try plan
          chette.^^StHß^^B^o96iQH''SK^
          "Now, if It were not already notorious
          that D— hail been a little soft on Smith's
          sweetheart of late we would have passed
          over this little incident as one of the
          vagaries of plancbette. But Smith couldn't
          take it in this light. He was crushed, and
          Invited D— to take his place. 1 needn't
          tell you that D— declined the invitation,
          but I would stake a small sum that" D—
          has his bands on a plancbette this moment.
          a,\*'l look Smith's place at the planchette
          and presently the' thing began ;to move
          again. This time it discarded the use of
          the alphabet and gave its message in writ
          ing.
          "Now, I am not going to place any reli
          ance on this thing till I see how it turns
          out, but the message that came to me is
          Important if it is true.
          '"I am an enemy,' it wrote.
          '"Are you going to thrash him?' asked
          Jone?, who likes to be facetious when
          there is the least call for it.
          ."'No!' said planchette. Then after a
          pause it carefully wrote out, '1 am going
          to harm him. He is my enemy and I will
          be revenged.'
          "Well, all this meant nothing without a
          name, and no name had been given yet.
          Again I asked for the name and ■it not
          only wrote oat the name of tbe man who
          happens to be smarting under a very just
          punishment that i Inflicted upon, him, but
          wrote it in bis own handwriting. a
          ''You should have seen some of the faces
          of the men who sal about that table when
          they recognized the handwriting. One of
          the men who bad laughed loudest and
          scoffed the most when we first sat down
          found it necessary to go outside for fresh
          air." There was no more laughter tbat
          evening. i
          "Then it came into my bead to ask plan
          chette something about itself, but before
          we put the questions both Jones and my
          self were blindfolded. This precaution is
          unnecessary, for it is simply impossible to
          move planchette as it does move without
          exerting a physical force that would be
          readily detected. However, we did this
          more to convince ourselves than others.
          ".'Are you inspired?' asked.
          "'Yes,' came the answer.
          'By a good power?'
          "The instrument fairly flew to the word
          'no.'
          'By the devil said Jones.
          'The devil,' it spelled out without the
          least hesitation. s:
          'Who are you?' I inquired.
          'An agent of the devil,' replied plan
          chetie, and this time in writing.
          "And after that there was not a man in
          the room brave enough to put bis hand on
          that instrument."
          The above questions and answers can
          be vouched for by -more than one man
          whose word in the commercial world is as
          good as his bond, and many similar dia
          logues might be cited to prove— prove
          well, to prove that plancbette has a strong
          hold on the people of this city once more.
          Whether the craze will die out before it
          reaches any great proportions again re
          mains to be seen.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1915-12-11/ed-1/?sp=17&amp;q=Marvelous+Mysterious+Messages+Talking+Patience+Worth+Curran+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Tho oulja board Is coming back
          tnto favor and has been taken up
          I quit extensively by society women
          v In New York, Boston, Chicago, St.
          Louis and various parts of the coun
          try. Perhaps tho most remarkable le-
          Iccnt experiences with it arc those of
          Mrs, John Curran of St, Louis. Sho
          has been in communication, she says,
          with the spirit of Patience Worth, a
          woman beliovcd to have existed in
          lhe Colonial days and who not only
          has sent philosophical axioms that
          are characteristic of tho Puritans
          but even has gone to tho extent of
          sending outlines of plays and es
          says and has gone extensively Into
          the dictation of poetry. More than
          300,000 words havo been received
          from this supposed spirit in ihieo
          years.
          Patience Worth talks In a strange
          t English that is archaic and not
          J 1 found in the best authors and yet
          j may have at one time been the
          tongue of Inhabitants of this coun
          try. Long condemned by religious as
          the direct agency of satan and by
          i skeptics as the toy of the supcrsti-
          tlous, the ouija board is being ro
          f stored to its own former popularity
          I through the curiosity of society wo
          men. In many parts of the country oo
          clety women are devoting their timo
          to "communicating" with spirits in
          tho other world.
          Many sti'ango results of such com
          munications are reported and a ao
          t clety woman is unhappy indeed if
          she hasn't at least one good spirit
          i in tho world of mystery who is al
          B ways ready to send a message at her
          m, control's pleasure.
          Ill Even in staid St. Louis where so-
          lit! cIety women arc supposed to bo
          1$ very conservative, tho ouija board
          il has been, restored to favor whilo
          HA
          in New York and In various
          cities of the east it is quite the
          "rage."
          In St Louis Mrs. John H. Curran
          has gotten into touch with one Pa
          tience Worth of Spiritland and has
          transcribed more than 300,000 words
          thiough the ouija board, all of which
          will be published at some future
          date.
          Patience Worth is believed from
          her peculiar choice of words and
          phraseology to be a Colonial dame,
          who has been wandering about In
          space for a long time, burning to
          send her messages back to the mun
          dane sphere yet finding no source of
          communication until Mrs. Curran
          bought a ouija board and com
          menced taking messages.
          THROUGH
          CURIOSITY.
          The board Avas purchased through
          curiosity. There is something fas
          cinating about the tales told of tho
          little board, whether they be- true
          or false. It is known that a num
          ber of people have asked the board
          to tell them in what land their dead
          iclativcs liugercd and were shocked
          considerable- when the naughty Utile
          hoard spelled out a word starling
          A ith an H and ending with an L.
          Many have thought that the words
          written bv the board were the result
          of the mental influences oC the per
          son opeiating it. while others have
          credited it with supernatural pow
          ers. In tho use of tho board at the Cur
          ran home, Mrs. Curran always is one
          of two whose "hands are on the
          board. The latter is arranged on
          two wheels and has a pencil at the
          end. As the vibration of the fingers
          of tho holders develops the pencil
          moves over a sheet of paper and
          prints numerals o'r letters of the al
          phabet, While Mrs. Curran operates tho
          board her husband transcribes tho
          message as sho reads it to him.
          The "Patience Worth" matter be
          gan to be transcribed in June, 1913.
          Since that time Mrs. Curran has
          made public as the products of Pa
          tience Worth a six-act play entitled
          "Red Wing." a novel called "Tclka"
          and numerous verses, essays and
          bits of philosiphy.
          The quaint language of these writ
          ings has probably attracted more at
          tention than their literary merit, tho
          latter being a matter of some dis
          cussion. They are in an antique
          language, not the English of Chau
          cer, Spenser or any other well-
          known classic English writer, but
          possibly more like the common
          speech of the English people of an
          early day.
          It is known to travelers that an
          antique, almost archaic, form of
          English still Is spoken in remote
          communities of England. Theie are
          districts of England whose inhabi
          tants have great difficulty in under
          standing or in making themselves
          understood by the coster-cockney
          class.
          Mrs. Curran, however, says sho
          has no personal acquaintance with
          such speech and that she has not
          gone farther in her study of classic
          English than other well read per
          sons. The language used' by Patience
          Worth, she explains, is as strange
          to her as It is to others.
          Mrs. Curran recently gave to the
          Fapyrus Club of St. Louis some of
          her messages from Patience Worth,
          one of them being a special messago
          that Patience had sent the club. It
          read:
          PATIENCE WORTH'S
          MESSAGE.
          Good Dames and SIrrahs At the
          board thou hast sat and cat of
          earth's grow. Aye, and now do ye
          cat o' the grow thou knowest not the
          looting place of. Yea, thou shalt
          hark unto the woid o' MEN, and jet
          they do to prate o' DAME. Ayca,
          and methlnks 'tis a word aspoke'
          amany, that be not the word that
          hid 'pon the lung, lest the Dame be
          offended I
          Aye, then come thou and ait 'bout
          the board, and thine cars shall hark
          tmto the words o' me, and thou shalt
          sec the cloth o' me the hands o' the
          loves o' mc did to fashion out for
          me. Ayea, I then shall sit me meek,
          and thread mc up a bobbins full for
          the next o' put.
          Ayca, and 'tis frocked that I shall
          to be, and nay dame shall see!
          Awoe! Nay, this be a piddlc-put-tlng,
          good folk!
          Athin (within) thy heart shall set
          the me o' me at thy go ahence. And
          'tis nhope I be 'tis a loving wampth
          'twill find. And so dost thou to
          smile, 'tis Bweets and love 1 cast
          thee. And doth thy heart to shut it
          up, lo, then shall I to knock till thou
          dost leave me in.
          A night o' cheer. A heart o' love!
          A God's wish o' loving 'pon thy day.
          Anight! Anight!
          HOW IT
          BEGAN.
          Mrs. Curran told her audience of
          her first experiences with tho ouija
          WW
          w
          board and of the puzzling messages
          received. Later sho used the'board
          together with Mrs Emily Grant
          Hutchings and began to receive
          sentences which foimcd maxims and
          philosophical paragrapbs. Then
          came the announcement:
          "Many moons ago I lived. Patience
          Worth, my namo. If thou shalt live
          then so shall I. I make my bread by
          thy hearth"
          The word "bread." Mrs. Currau
          later learned, lefeired to the literary
          products embodied in the messages.
          Mrs. Curran said she would not at
          tempt to say whelhcr Patience
          Worth was a spirit, but spoko of ,ber
          as a beautiful personality, which had
          come to seem not a mystery but a
          fellowship.
          She said the messages came to her
          in daylight as well as at night and
          that there is no trance connected
          with them.
          "The words come in sort o a
          rhythm," Mrs. Curran explained,
          "and I record just what comes
          whether I understand it or not."
          Pnticuce has been tested by rnoro
          than 200 persons and her messages
          have never varied. A professor from
          the University of Indiana visltod
          Mrs. Cunan to investigate her com
          munication with Patience Worth.
          William Marion' Reedy, editor of
          the Mirror, and Caspar Yost, editor
          of a SL Louis newspaper, became ac
          quainted with Patience Worth and
          both declaic her genuine. Yost has
          described her as a "spinster of un
          certain age; a writer, but a poet by
          preference. White the average spirit
          stalks dismal and wailing lugubri
          ously through the flnito world, Pa
          tience comes with a laugh, Yost said.
          She remarks. ''I be no sorrj' singer,"
          and proves it by many witticisms.
          EDITOR
          DESCRIBES HER.
          Reedy calls Patience's doctrines
          Pantelstic.
          He describes her as follows: "She
          fs a little woman, dressed In gtaj;
          with a little bonnet, ribbons coming
          down and tied under her chin. There
          are lines in her face, not the re
          written wrinkles of the smiles or
          her youth, but the results of ex
          perience Her eyes are biown liico
          autumn leaves after a rain. She Is
          -between 45 and 50 years old, spright
          ly, dainty, delicate.
          "Sho has stood beside the stock
          ade helping a good man load a gun,
          while he defends the settlement
          against the savage horde of In
          dians." Reedy said the theory was ad
          vanced that she was filled in an In
          dian massacre and this question was
          askcu of her. Sho intimated that
          something of this sort had happened
          to her and she was asked if she had
          not been taken captive oy the In
          dians. "Nay, something worse," was her
          reply.
          '.'She speaks an English almost
          pure and undefiled," Reedy said of
          her "There is an absence from it
          of all the derivatives of France and
          Rome, and sho rarely uses a word
          of more than two syllables. Her an
          swers are- diredt and almost invari
          ably in parables. She has respect
          for her interlocutor's intelligence."
          Reedy said sho is not another
          Sappho, or George Elliott, or Mrs.
          Humphrey ward nor a Sara Teas
          dale,' but rather echoes of all of thct
          poets. He said theie runs a consist
          ent character through her works and
          in two years she has not gotten "out
          of chaiactcr." Sho never has used a
          modern word or expression and he
          illustrated the seeming significance
          of this by pointing out how difficult
          it would be for a man trained In
          Irish or negro dialect to make a 30
          minute talk without breaking out of
          the character.
          "She has nothing lo tell, in my
          opinion, "Reedy said, "but she com
          mands my admiration and reverence.
          She tells nothing- that we have not
          heard from tho old masters and
          bards."
          "What of the divinity of Christ?"
          Kcody at one time asked her through
          the ouijd board. She answered, "He
          bought thee of his loving."
          "What of love?" he asked. "Tho
          love there is but tho o'er drip of lovo
          here" came the respou&amp;c of tho
          board.
          "Describe tho place where you
          are?" sho was asked. "Think you
          "Patience Worth," Mythical
          Character, Startles Literary
          World With Her Quaint I
          English In Essays, Plays and H
          Novels Noted Writers Are H
          Puzzled Over the Output of H
          This Woman Supposed to H
          Have i Lived 300 Years Ago H
          there Is bottom or top; this is a
          walless country."
          "Can you do anything you want
          over there 7" The answer was:
          "When you put the will you put the
          limit."
          "Put" in Patience's vocabulary re
          sponds to the modern verb "to do."
          "Patience may be a second person
          ality of Mrs. Curran," -Reedy sato.
          "but she teaches a lovo that is
          greater than we can conceive and
          that death is the keeper of unknown
          redemption."
          LITTLE COLONIAL
          DAME.
          Mrs. Emily Hutchings, who -was
          one of the first to receive 'with Mrs.
          Curran the messages from Patlenco
          Worth, said the first glimmering or
          the quaint personality of the little
          Colonial dame came in the maxim:
          "A busy saw gathereth no rust."
          One of the sentiments expressed
          by Patience Worth is: "A blighted
          bud may hold a sweeter message
          than the lovllest flower; for God
          hath kissed her wounded heart and
          left a promise there."
          Of the seances, Mrs. Curran says:
          "I sit with a friend, our hands up
          on the board, which I havo come to
          believe is nothing more than a con
          centrator. There is no trance. Ev
          erything is quiet with the exception
          of Patience Worth. The only
          definite part is that while I put my
          thoughts awhither, as Patience
          would Bay, and immediately the sto
          ries, poems, plays., parables, or
          whatever her work for the sitting IH
          may be, is shown to mo in tiny pic- JH
          lures, beautiful and distinct a3 IH
          though my eyes saw them.
          "The characters move and speak H
          and my hands fly over the letters jH
          much too fast for me to anticipate- H
          even one word. J
          "I cannot account for the langu- jH
          age. The words seem to be spoken ilH
          to me. though I cannot 'say 1 hear llH
          them In the sense that we hear tho iH
          voice that speaks aloud to us. The H
          words come m sort of a rhythm. I lH
          am not familiar with old Euglish jH
          and yet even the conversations -are H
          in this archaic tongue." jH
          Psychologists recently havetakcn ,H
          up a" study of Mrs. Curran and tho M
          Mvstcrlous Patience Worth. Some jM
          believe that Paticnco Worth is Mrs. jH
          Curran's sub-conscious self. Others jH
          have departed in doubt and without jH
          expressing an opinion. iH
          The ouija board has been con- JH
          demned by various religious bodies, iH
          but society is taking it up beside il
          these prohibitions. The Catholic tl
          church has condemned it as a super-
          stitlous practice. H
          Other religious bodies havo u- H
          clarcd that the devil is in hc boaid H
          and employs it to send his messages. H
          Whatever the truth may be, so-
          ciety has gone into the mystery of lH
          tho board, not so much with the ob- iH
          jeet of definitely deciding if it really jH
          is the medium of communication H
          with the other world but to,gratlfy H
          society's chief attribute Curiosity. H
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1915-12-12/ed-1/?sp=33&amp;q=Patience+Worth+Curran+Spirit+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96076839/1920-06-25/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Invented+William+Isaac+Fuld+Baltimore+Dispute+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          WHO INVENTED OUIJA
          Brothers Ask Baltimore Court to
          Settle Dispute.
          Brothers, Apparently Lacking Falfh
          In Talking Board, Ask Judge
          to Decide.
          Baltimore. At the moment that the
          oulja board, which some years ago ex-
          cited the country and then virtually
          disappeared, has again come Into the
          Umellgbt throughout the world, two
          brothers are engaged In litigation here
          over the ownership of the patent, t
          The trial Is now In progress of the
          suit of Isaac Fuld, trading as the
          Southern Toy company, who I ask
          ing for an Injunction to restrain his
          brother, William Fuld, from deriving
          pecuniary profits through the sale of
          the oulja board.
          The plaintiff asserts that In 1904 he
          originated, manufactured and placed
          upon the market the board under the
          copyright name of the oracle 'and
          that later William Fuld started the
          manufacture of ihe oulja board.
          William Fuld asserts that he and
          Isaac Fuld were In business together
          years ago, and that the oulja board
          Is the original talking board, and
          claims that tlie oracle talking board
          manufactured by Isaac Fuld Is a
          copy of the one placed on the market
          by him.
          The Fulds about 28 years ago were
          In charge of a wooden toy factory
          known as the Kennard Manufacturing
          company, and the oulja board was one
          of the devicesthey made to entertain
          the young. It quickly won tremen
          dous popularity nnd so overshadowed
          the business of tho concern that the
          plant was largely devoted to the mak
          ing of. the oulja board.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1920-01-25/ed-1/?sp=32&amp;q=Baby+Ghost+Spectral+Messages+Curran+Patience+Worth+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          These entertaining and ravther well written novels
          War? dictated by the spirit of "Patience Worth" to
          Mrs. John Curran, of St. Louis, Mra. Curran solemn
          ly Ms?trta. Mrs. Curran says aha wrote every word of
          that? novels and many poem* on a ouija board word
          fttr word as the spectral voice of "Patience Worth"
          whiipered them in her ear. t
          shit theae spooky novel? ?ire not what this page
          deals with to-*lay. ?A nor? oaereet?ng thing to being
          done by this spook, .vccortllng to Mra. Curran and
          her friends. 'Patience Worth" oommividtTsd Mra.
          Curran, who ia childless, to seSarch for a certain rad
          head*id, blue eyed infant "with dark linea in than."
          whoee father was English and mother waa Scsotoh.
          Such a baby waa found and adopted by Mra.
          Curran
          And thia child, embodying to-day features and
          parentage similar to "Patience Worth," who tited 200
          years ago, is being brought up by ita spectral god
          mother Day by day "Patience Worth" gives Mra.
          Curran an ouija board message of advice about little
          Patienoe Worth Wee whenever il to U4&gt;?*mI4mL
          Three-year-old Patience
          Worth Wee, iron* re
          cent photograph of tho
          ghost-guided lituo ono
          ia Forest Park, St.
          Louis, She is wearing
          tho clothing ordered by
          hot "spirit mother."
          SIX years ago Mrs. John H Curran, of St. Louis, a
          peculiarly healthy-minded, normal young woman,
          who is the wife of the former Immigration Commis
          sioner of Misitvouri, began for amusement to experiment
          with the ouija board. This peculiar instrument for receiv
          ing meaaages foom the beyond" consists of a flat wooden
          board, about two feet long by one and a half wide, on
          which are th? letters of the alphabet, the numerala up to
          ten and the words ''Yea," "Mo," "Don't know" and
          "Good-by." A little heart-shaped table on three legs is
          placed on top of the board. The sitters place the board
          upon their knees, the finger tips of both hands lightly upon
          the heart-shaped table. After a while an "influence,"
          "apirit" or "spook" begins to move the heart-shaped
          board, whose narrow end then points to the letters, spell
          ing out the words of ?ta* message. A third person, an
          observer, acts as amenuensis, taking down the letters as
          the pointer indicates them.
          The "mestages" are accounted for by non-spiritualista
          as an expression of the sub-conscious self of one or both
          of the sitters; the mysterious movement of the table is
          supposed to be due to unconscious muscle rhythms of the
          hands of the sitters.
          Whatever the explanation, Mrs. Curran began to hear
          from someone who signed herself "Patience Worth" and
          who spelled out upon the board sentences in remarkable
          English?archaic, a forgotten dialect. This ghostly per
          sonage speedily developed into the strongest kind of a
          personality. She had been, she wrote, a maiden of Dor
          setshire. England, who lived about 1650. She was a
          weaver's daughter, an only child. She wrote that "my
          thumb is thick from twisting flax" and speaks of deliver
          ing fine linen to the "castle folk." Her father left to
          come to America, and after the death of her mother.
          Patience says she followed him to the new world. ?She
          was then thirty-five. Her new home was in the vicinity
          of Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket. Near there she
          tv a? buried, and now, she says, "a tree grows out of my
          grave."
          Soon she began to dictate stories and poems with ex
          traordinary rapidity and facility. The first book pub
          lished was "Patience Worth." The "Sorry Tale," a
          story based on the episode of the impenitent thief on Ihe
          cross, came out in 1916 and "Hope Trueblood." the last
          book, was a story of old England.
          The remarkable literary excellence of these writings
          attracted widespread attention. Their dialect
          passed every teat of experts. It was proven that
          Mrs. Curran had no previous knowledge of them,
          nor had she the education displayed by the com
          munications. Dr. Martin F. Prince, the famous
          neurologist, diagnosed Patience "asa sub-conscious
          personality of Mrs. Curran and offered to rid her of it
          by hypnotism. Mrs. Curran refused to have "Patience"
          banished by this means or any other, and scoffs at the
          sub conscious theory. Other distinguished scientists
          studied her case, but with no better results.
          For three years the "ghost" of Patience Worth?or
          whatever it is that responda to that nam?2?had been dic
          tating to Mrs. Curran by means of the oirija board as a
          concentrator. One book had been printed, another waa
          on the way to the printer. The first book was already
          promising an excellent sale. Reviews had been flattering
          and the publie was becoming interested
          Then one evening, after the Currans had been' dis
          cussing this materialistically agreeable result of the.man
          ifestations, Patience Worth exploded a bombshell. In
          the quaint old English words which she uses she an
          nounced that inasmuch an there "seemed to be some
          money in sight." and since it did not belong to the Cur
          rans. "but to God," that they should seek "a wee babe
          that had nothing, nothing and take it and care for iti"
          This was. indeed, disconcerting. The Curran house
          was a well-filled one. There was a grandfather, a mother
          in-law, a stepdaughter and the husband and wife. Be
          sides, they had counted upon using the money for thorn
          selves.
          Patience, however, was determined and explicit. Sho
          caustically called attention to the fact that the emolu
          menta of her bock did not belong to those who simply
          took down her dictation, but that as the author and main
          spring of the volume the returns from it were hers to do
          with aa she Dleased.
          "I am a weaver of cloth," said Patience on that night,
          in the curious imagery she loves to use, "and this cloth
          weave is not for him who hath. Thou ehalt seek a wee
          one who hath naught, and thou shalt deliver the goods
          of me unto it? hands, and ye shalt speak ita name
          ?Patience Worth."*
          This was an order, not a request 1 And to it when the
          first shock of surprise had worn off the Currans gladly
          bowed.
          ??L?ook ye.'' the '^heat** went on, "this shall be one
          who is sorely in need, mind ye Ye ?hall whisper sweets
          unto it. even unto the wee ear that knoweth not thy
          words, and tell unto it of a fairy dame who shall minister
          unto it and of Him who sent her And she shell be the
          love of all who love me and shall smile sweeta unto
          them.*'
          "But why a girl instead of a boyt" the Currans aaked
          anxiously.
          "Ye aee,'* answered Patience cryptically enough, "a
          man laddie hath man'? cunning, but the wee dame??ah,
          I know I"
          The Curran? quite naturally asked about the parent
          age of the child, ita legitimacy and many other important
          things, not the least of which was a description of it so
          that they might know when they bad found tbe babe
          Patience had in mind
          She gave them certain directions???rather vague; told
          them "not to mind earth's law but God's"?referring
          unquestionably to the matter of parentage and to watch
          close if there were any blood taints, but not to go back
          further than the grandparent?.. She wanted the child
          dressed simply, she concluded, and asked thai "about its
          neck thou ?halt hang a sign of Him." The Curran?, and
          rightly it, turned out later, construed this to mean
          cross."
          "Ye shall be upon tbe path! E'en now the wee one
          is waiting," she urged.
          So the hunt began for a child who wouid answer the
          description. The entire "Patience Worth" clan was sent
          out on the seareh. Two physicians were selected to ex
          amine it when found for blood taint! Much ground wa?
          covered in the next month. There were handicaps?an
          interesting one the refusal by a certain large St. Louis
          foundling institution to allow any baby to be taken from
          there because "Mrs. Curran wrote on a ouija board."
          During this search "Patience," who seems to have a
          strange sense of humor at times, remained silent. Then
          one night, according to Mrs. Curran, she directed them
          to cease, telling them there was no use in looking for
          "one that was not whole," and that in due time certain
          signs would be given them whereby they would know
          what to do adding that if they did continue it would be
          "like a wolf seeking for a fat fowl to feed well upon
          when the bird was still in the egg." After this, other
          weeks passed by without any reference being made by
          "Patience Worth" to the matter.
          Then one morning Mrs. Curran met an old friend
          whom she had not seen for years, and in the course of a
          ride together told some of the details of the quest for the
          baby. The friend, in return, told of a young wife who
          was about to become a mother, who was practically home
          less and friendless, and whose husband had been killed
          some time before in a mill accident. That night g mes
          sage from "Patience Worth" indicated that at last the
          Curraros were on the right track and that which she had
          prophesied M'as about to occur.
          The next day Mrs. Curran went to see this woman,
          who was very ill. A fever of preparation began imme
          diately. Layette cradle, perambulator, lawyers, adoption
          papers?everything was made ready just as though the
          thing were already settled. Seemingly the possibility
          that the expected child might be a boy was never for a
          moment considered.
          The mother-to-be signed the adoption papers, but held
          them under the agreement that if she lived she was to
          keep the expected child, but that if she died, then the
          Currans were to have the baby.
          Six weeks later, as Mrs Curran was writing with
          "Patience" upon the now well-known "Sorry Tale," the
          "ghost" stopped the dictation at exactly nine o'clock.
          "This be enough," she wrote, and the board became
          quiet.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063381/1920-02-24/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Revelation+Lawsuit+Albert+Yost+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          REVELATION OF OUIJA
          FORMS BASIS OF LAW SUIT
          Lockport, 111., Feb. 24.An Ouija
          board and its uncanny revelations
          form the basis of a $10,000 suit here
          against Albert Yost. Recently Yost's
          home was burglarized. An Ouija
          board was consulted to solve the mys
          tery surrounding the robbery. Answ
          ering the question "Who robbed my
          house?" the board is said to have
          replied "Frank Walter." Walter is
          Yost's neighbor. They have been
          lifelong friends. The board is also
          said to have implicated Mrs. Walter.
          The board's accusations became
          known to Mrs. Walter, who called at
          the Yost home. She was told the
          Yosts had nothing to retract and
          forthwith filed suit for $10,000
          against Yosts, alleged slander. The
          Yosts deny the charge and insist they
          have uttered no word which might be
          interpreted as defaming the charac
          ter of the Walters.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1920-11-14/ed-1/?sp=70&amp;q=Invades+Britain+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Ouija Board Invades Britain
          LONDON, Nov. 10.
          THE ouija board has invaded
          Britain! It masquerades un?
          der the pseudonym of "plan?
          chette," but it is the familiar
          alphabet and flatiron device that has
          helped to while away the tedium of
          prohibition in the United States.
          And apparently it has landed in
          force, because even now officials of
          women's clubs are debating as to
          whether the planchette is a game,
          or, if it isn't, what it is.
          "If it is a game." argued one club
          secretary, "it should be played as a
          game In the cardroom and during
          the regulation card hours. As it is,
          the planchette enthusiasts are busily
          occupied with their favorite pastime
          from early morn to dewy eve."
          Although she waxed poetic at the
          end, it was evident that the official
          was really disturbed about the exact
          status of the planchette. F-&gt;r it is
          said that the fascinating business of
          receiving messages from the spin*
          world?not the s?ance which was w
          popular following the war, but the
          more informal question-and-answer
          of the ouija board?is quite ousting
          the card games.
          If no regulation planchette is at
          hand a substitute, consisting of ?B
          ordinary inverted tumbler surround?
          ed by cardboard letters, is CtB*
          into play. The fingers are pl??*11
          upon the bottom of this glass, j^*
          as they are upon the little triant"
          lar device of the real ouija boaru.
          and it skips lightly from one letf*r
          to another spelling out its message*.
          And the planchette is less ex?
          pensive than bridge, because no on*
          yet has thought of betting on tM
          spirits! -?j
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1921-10-26/ed-1/?sp=22&amp;q=Mental+Troubles+Phenomena+Mystisms+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Mental Trounble i
          Washington?
          By BILL PRICE.
          Whether there is truth in a statmmnt that the ouija
          board is adding patients to Wasinta asums
          through disturbing infinenoes augon District mentalitin,
          students of mental phenomena will be inteAsted in the
          fact that the board takes its name from the French
          word oui (yes) and the German word ja (yes). Its
          origin is somewhat obscure. Both the planohette and
          ouija, somewhat simila in appearanes, date back to
          about 1855, and for a while were objects of consider
          able superstition. The planchette is a small board
          fitted with a pencil and two casters, made to move
          easily over a sheet of paper when the hands rest lightly
          on it. The dictionary says the ouija "is a form of
          planchatte used in spiritualistic seaness or the like.
          It consists of two parts, a board containing the al
          phabet and other characters, and a planehette, with
          a pointer substituted for the pencil."
          Investigation of automatic writings fail to find that
          the two boards have any origin in the mysticisms of
          Egypt. One writer is of the opinion that the iret at
          tempt in ouijaing was made by a man on his wife's
          breadboard. The skeptical refer to the board as
          wholly a modem trick afair which has no connection
          with Eastern or other metaphysics.
          Some of the noted spiritualists of the world make use
          of the ouija or planchette and carefully study the
          results. An able group of psychologists regard the
          ouija as a dangerous deception. Their theory is that
          the subconscious mind of the operator directs the
          fingers in such a way as to convey the information
          hoped for. The operator, they hold, is as innocent of
          this subconscious process as a sleep-walker is of what,
          he is doing, and naturally puts a supernatural con
          struction on the outcome.
          Leading spiritualists and other believers in higher
          agencies than natural ones, confident that communica
          tion with the other world is not only established but
          is developing into an understanding that will glorify
          humanity, are willing to accept the ouija board or any
          other method of transmission that will add ti the in
          formation they feel they now possess. Those of ma
          terial minds, who deride all supernatural beliefs and
          theories, hold to the opinion that after every great
          war there is a wave of the occult in some form, and
          say that right now the ouija board happens to be the g
          most popular man-made medium of bringing together
          terrestrial pinds and celestial beings and thoughts.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86064187/1917-09-26/ed-1/?sp=27&amp;q=ouija+ghost</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          ALARM IS GIVEN
          BY OUIJA BOARD
          OF MAN IN ROOM
          Ghost May Testify in Unique
          Indiana Case.
          rVANSVILLK. Ind -Hire a gW to
          warn yuu of danger and jruard yoa
          from injury!
          A spirit protector, speaking throaffb
          the onija board, warned two F.varts
          ytlle women against a man's attack.
          The intruder lay three feet away, under
          their bed, and listened to the alarm
          message he waj powerless to prevent.
          May Prore Existence In Court.
          The Evansville ghost expect to
          prove his existence in court hy law.
          lie w ill not remain a creature of hear
          say, to be believed in or scoffed at ac
          cording to whether meti are credulous
          cr skeptical about the reality of the
          pi rit world.
          And all F.vansville asks this
          "What kind of a witness will a ghost
          make when the ouija board puts in its
          first recorded appearance in court?"
          Mrs. Martha Place and her daughter,
          JAargarrt, 811 John street, lonely, took
          up thair miija hoard to find they were
          nt as much alone as they had thought.
          "l ook out for Nat and Harb," spelled
          the board.
          A htrec blew back the curtains of
          Ihe bedroom where the women sat.
          "It's a little cooler," said Mrs. Place
          go her daughter.
          Board Repeats Warning.
          The curtains, an they billowed in,
          touched the bed beneath which lay the
          man. He held his breath as he heard
          the ghost messenger warn the two
          V"ien against him.
          "Is this Henry?" Mrs. Place asked
          the board.
          "Yes! Look out for Nat and Itarb!"
          repeated the board
          Henry is a son of Mrs. Place, electro
          killed ten years ago.
          "I have told vou before, Henry,"
          fcaid Mrs. Place, shaking a reproving
          linger at the tripod Vhich had spelled
          out the warning message by darting
          from one letter if the alphabet to an
          other, "not to talk that way,ahout the
          Moxleys." Nathanial anil Barbara
          Moxley, living .across the street, were
          the "Nat and Harb," of the ghostly
          Warning.
          Nothing Use Sail
          The board would say nothing further,
          kxcrpt repetitions of its ghostly alarm.
          The two women put the board away
          RihI went to bed.
          Mrs. Place heard a noise, like a
          leratching on the matting under the
          led. It was the cat, she and her
          daughter thought.
          Again Mrs. Place heard the noire. It
          ras not the cat. She leaped Trom bed
          and i an into the kitchen for a match.
          Margaret screamed. Trrere was the
          sound of a body falling.
          "I inn back toward the bedroom."
          Mrs. Place told the police later. "A
          man dashed past me through the kitch
          en into the garden. I followed. It
          was Nathaniel Moxley.
          Paper round on Floor.
          "We found a paper on the floor. He
          must have dropped it crawling from
          beneath the bed. It was a summons
          to Nathaniel Moxley to appear in court
          as witness in a divorce case. We Rave
          it to the police. They arrested him
          "When everything was quiet we took
          gmt the ouija board again.
          'I told you to look out for Nat and
          ttarb,' Henry spelled. And there the
          man was, under the bed within reach.
          While we were warned."
          Nathaniel Moxley has been bound
          giver to the grand jury.
          If the ouija board is asked to he ex
          libit in the grand jury room a new
          era in court procedure will be ushered
          The cross-examination of a ghost is
          judicial novelty.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88064384/1918-04-27/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=ghost+board</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86076201/1920-03-27/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=ouija+ghost</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Ouija-Board Silliness
          It has been said that the average newspaper reporter is
          just as honest and reliable as the average person that he inter
          views. We accept this as true so long as the person inter
          viewed is present in the flesh, but when it comes to the honesty
          and reliability of those persons who communicate with the de
          parted spirits, we draw the line. There we halt. An inter
          view with a pencil and pad as the mediums is something reason
          able, but when the pencil and pad are thrown away, and a
          table or ouija board duplicated, then the thing begins to look
          spooky. And—just think—you could quote the poor spirit
          anyway you wanted to, and yet he, it, or she, would have no
          recourse, except possibly by haunting you. And anyone hav
          ing the nerve to hold a telepathic conflab with a spirit would be
          above fearing a ghost. Senator Sorghum in the flesh could
          scare the editor into making a correction, or a retraction, but
          how could a spirit institute libel proceedings against anyone?
          There is some credulity behind even the most serious scien
          tific facts, especially in the earlier stages of their development.
          But there is considerable difference between a speck of credul
          ity and a great expanse of human gullibility. Any violent dis
          turbance, like the great war, tends to distort people’s emotions
          and reason, even more than it does their action and will. This
          must be the explanation of the tidal wave oi spiritualism that
          is now sweeping this country. The revers >n to the belief in
          the existence of ghosts is simply the bringing into pronounced
          relief of the state of mind that our ancestors exhibited. The
          burning of witches at Salem was of its fruitage. Spiritualism
          is superstition curtailed by law. As its disciples no longer
          have access to the stake and the guillotine, they must amuse
          themselves as best they can with table-rappings, ouija boards,
          and other such paraphernalia.
          The fact that such men a3 Sir Richard Crookes and Sir
          Oliver Lodge are converts to spiritualism gives little support to
          the hoax, for even a layman can find serious flaws in their evi
          dence, and such men as Joseph Jastrow and Sir Edward Clodd
          can veritably tear their tenets to shreds. From its inception,
          spiritualism has been founded on trickery and frauds, and no
          proof has yet been brought forward showing that the present
          revival is not concocted of the same ingredients. Even if such
          were not the case, we have our hands full of problems as it is,
          without giving heed to the imaginary gibbering of disembodied
          ghosts.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86075258/1950-05-31/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=ouija+ghost</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
          Ghost of Highworth Rd.
          Returns After Exorcism
          BRISTOL. ENGLAND. "Mrs.
          It," the ghost of 13 Highworth rd.,
          is back again—with a playmate.
          Only recently the haunt was ex
          orcized by a Church of England
          vicar in a religious rite to drive
          away spirits taken from early
          Cristian records.
          The peace of No. 13 was short
          lived. Mr. and Mrs. William Ba
          ber, who live in the house, say the
          ghost now does a nightly routine
          up and down the stairs with an
          unidentified partner. Sometimes
          it sounds like they're dancing,
          sometimes like wrestling.
          The Baber theory is that the
          original ghost—which they named
          "Mrs. It"—is that of a woman who
          died in the house 18 years ago.
          "Mrs. It" first began prowling
          around the place in December.
          The vicar, the Rev. Francis
          Maddock, went through a rite of
          exorcism after a month of nightly
          uproar at No. 13.
          One night the Babers called in a
          spiritualist. All they found out is
          that "Mrs. It" (1) speaks a foreign
          language—possibly Russian and
          (2) is an atrocious speller.
          A ouija board was used to see
          if she had any message. What
          came out was "EEHFHMEV."
          Try Dancing if Putting
          Child to Sleep Difficult
          Gene
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053323/1894-10-27/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=ghost+board</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>

    </results>

  </topic>
</topics>